<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Forum Moved To: rebol.metaeducation.com</title>
    <link>https://rebol.metaeducation.com/t/forum-moved-to-rebol-metaeducation-com/2408</link>
    <description>Visit the new location here:

**[https://rebol.metaeducation.com](https://rebol.metaeducation.com)**

## Why Move?

DNS for `rebol.info` stopped resolving, and it&#39;s not under our control.

## Why Was rebol.info Used To Begin With?

I actually resisted having a forum, and it was @gchiu who went ahead and did it anyway.

`rebol.info` was something used by the Rebol community whenever they wanted a free subdomain.  People with accounts could add the domain and where to point it, and that saved you from having to pay for a top-level domain for some random project.

But as interest in Rebol has waned over the years, the accountability at the top of whoever is control of `rebol.info` is gone.  In the past when there have been hiccups we&#39;ve sort of shuffled emails around to try and figure out how to get it to work, and eventually it has come back.

This time when it went down, I decided to just go ahead and relocate the forum as a subdomain under `metaeducation.com`, a domain that I own.  *(It was purchased many decades ago for a much different purpose, but curiously the meta-representational concept has become very crucial to the design of Ren-C.)*

## Is This The Final Location?

Unlikely.  But at least this way I control it, and when it needs relocating I can do the redirects.

## What About Forwarding Old Links?

Not sure if rebol.info is coming back, and if it does I&#39;m not quite sure if I&#39;d be able to forward the links here.

I used a command-line tool to search-and-replace the posts in the forum so that all the internal links should be fixed up.  If you find one that is not, let me know.

There are links in the codebase itself and I&#39;ll fix those too.

Other than that, we&#39;ve been intentionally under the radar on Google and such, so there shouldn&#39;t be many places with broken links.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 04:37:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Announcements</category>
    <atom:link href="https://rebol.metaeducation.com/t/forum-moved-to-rebol-metaeducation-com/2408.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Forum Moved To: rebol.metaeducation.com</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Visit the new location here:</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://rebol.metaeducation.com">https://rebol.metaeducation.com</a></strong></p>
<h2><a name="p-8133-why-move-1" class="anchor" href="https://rebol.metaeducation.com#p-8133-why-move-1"></a>Why Move?</h2>
<p>DNS for <code>rebol.info</code> stopped resolving, and it's not under our control.</p>
<h2><a name="p-8133-why-was-rebolinfo-used-to-begin-with-2" class="anchor" href="https://rebol.metaeducation.com#p-8133-why-was-rebolinfo-used-to-begin-with-2"></a>Why Was rebol.info Used To Begin With?</h2>
<p>I actually resisted having a forum, and it was <a class="mention" href="https://rebol.metaeducation.com/u/gchiu">@gchiu</a> who went ahead and did it anyway.</p>
<p><code>rebol.info</code> was something used by the Rebol community whenever they wanted a free subdomain.  People with accounts could add the domain and where to point it, and that saved you from having to pay for a top-level domain for some random project.</p>
<p>But as interest in Rebol has waned over the years, the accountability at the top of whoever is control of <code>rebol.info</code> is gone.  In the past when there have been hiccups we've sort of shuffled emails around to try and figure out how to get it to work, and eventually it has come back.</p>
<p>This time when it went down, I decided to just go ahead and relocate the forum as a subdomain under <code>metaeducation.com</code>, a domain that I own.  <em>(It was purchased many decades ago for a much different purpose, but curiously the meta-representational concept has become very crucial to the design of Ren-C.)</em></p>
<h2><a name="p-8133-is-this-the-final-location-3" class="anchor" href="https://rebol.metaeducation.com#p-8133-is-this-the-final-location-3"></a>Is This The Final Location?</h2>
<p>Unlikely.  But at least this way I control it, and when it needs relocating I can do the redirects.</p>
<h2><a name="p-8133-what-about-forwarding-old-links-4" class="anchor" href="https://rebol.metaeducation.com#p-8133-what-about-forwarding-old-links-4"></a>What About Forwarding Old Links?</h2>
<p>Not sure if rebol.info is coming back, and if it does I'm not quite sure if I'd be able to forward the links here.</p>
<p>I used a command-line tool to search-and-replace the posts in the forum so that all the internal links should be fixed up.  If you find one that is not, let me know.</p>
<p>There are links in the codebase itself and I'll fix those too.</p>
<p>Other than that, we've been intentionally under the radar on Google and such, so there shouldn't be many places with broken links.</p>
          <p><a href="https://rebol.metaeducation.com/t/forum-moved-to-rebol-metaeducation-com/2408/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://rebol.metaeducation.com/t/forum-moved-to-rebol-metaeducation-com/2408/1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 04:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">rebol.metaeducation.com-post-2408-1</guid>
        <source url="https://rebol.metaeducation.com/t/forum-moved-to-rebol-metaeducation-com/2408.rss">Forum Moved To: rebol.metaeducation.com</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
