<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>AltRebol - Latest topics</title>
    <link>https://forum.rebol.info/latest</link>
    <description>Latest topics</description>
    
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 09:05:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="https://forum.rebol.info/latest.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <item>
          <title>Singular ANY-SPACE vs. Plural WHITESPACE?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Naming</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Transitions have made some parse rules get longer:</p>
<pre><code> [any whitespace]  ; being repurposed--seems like "pick one" not a loop construct
 =&gt;
 [while whitespace]  ; being repurposed to arity-2; arity-1 form is unsettling
 =&gt;
 [opt some whitespace]  ; null if rule doesn't match, a little ugly
 =&gt;
 [maybe some whitespace]  ; void if rule doesn't match, longer but prettier
</code></pre>
<p>I like MAYBE and I've explained the reasons why I like pulling the optionality out from the looping construct.</p>
<p>But this seems a bit overlong...especially considering that whitespace is such a long word.</p>
<p>It occurs to me that "whitespace" can be itself plural.  Might we say that ANY-SPACE is a character set, and then <strong><code>whitespace: [some any-space]</code></strong> ?</p>
<p>This at least gets you down to <strong><code>[maybe whitespace]</code></strong> or <strong><code>[opt whitespace]</code></strong>...which seems pretty minimal for the intent (unless you're going to go with abbreviations like <strong><code>ws*</code></strong> or similar).</p>
<p>I really don't know how many cases there are where you are willing to tolerate only a single unit of an arbitrary whitespace character.  When does that come up?  Usually if you're matching a single whitespace character you know which one you're reacting to...and the only time you'd ever bundle up a collection of them together is when you're willing to skip a lot of it.</p>
<p>I doubt there'd be many uses of ANY-SPACE in a rule, and that it would just be used to compound other character collections.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/singular-any-space-vs-plural-whitespace/1828">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/singular-any-space-vs-plural-whitespace/1828</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 09:05:29 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1828</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/singular-any-space-vs-plural-whitespace/1828.rss">Singular ANY-SPACE vs. Plural WHITESPACE?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>undefined vs. null in JavaScript</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Foreign Inspiration</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>JavaScript distinguishes "undefined" and "null" in something of the way that ~unset~ and NULL are distinct.  An undefined variable is one you haven't assigned yet, NULL is one you've set to NULL.</p>
<pre><code>// Chrome Console Session
&gt; asdf
VM66:1 Uncaught ReferenceError: asdf is not defined

&gt; typeof asdf
&lt;- "undefined"

&gt; asdf = null
&lt;- null

&gt; asdf
&lt;- null

&gt; typeof asdf
&lt;- "object"
</code></pre>
<p><em>(If you're curious why the <strong>typeof</strong> null is an object in JavaScript: <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/18808226/why-is-typeof-null-object">"Because the spec says so.  This is generally regarded as a mistake."</a>.  The move of not having an answer for the value of the type, e.g. saying the answer to <strong>type of null</strong> is null - is much better)</em></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/undefined-vs-null-in-javascript/1826">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/undefined-vs-null-in-javascript/1826</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 11:22:56 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1826</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/undefined-vs-null-in-javascript/1826.rss">undefined vs. null in JavaScript</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Contemplating UPARSE-VALUE</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Parsing</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Once upon a time, PARSE was willing to take rules that were not BLOCK! and do "simple parsing".  Ultimately this was thought better of and became SPLIT...because that wasn't a very interesting polymorphism.</p>
<p>But... since PARSE is at heart a matching task, it seems there might be more accommodation when the input value is not a block... and you want to do some top level pattern matching.  Consider something like this:</p>
<pre><code>case [
     integer? item [
         print "Not a series, so, have to write handling code here"
     ]
     text? item [
         print "A series, but maybe we want to do something else"
     ]
     block? item [
         print "Okay finally we can use the parse we mean..."
         uparse item [...rules...]
     ]
] else [
   fail "Whatever"
]
</code></pre>
<p>It's something of a missed opportunity, and when I see this I start thinking along these lines:</p>
<pre><code>uparse reduce [item] [
     integer! &lt;end&gt; (print "More convenient, perhaps...")
         |
     text! &lt;end&gt; (print "Depends on the use case...")
         |
     into block! &lt;end&gt; [
        (print "Your rules here I guess...")
     ]
] else [
    fail "Whatever"
]
</code></pre>
<p>On first glance it's not necessarily an improvement, but... let's say for a minute that we have a UPARSE-VALUE which implicitly throws in the <code>&lt;end&gt;</code>:</p>
<pre><code>uparse-value item [
     integer! (print "Okay, this...")
         |
     text! (print "Seems a bit cleaner...")
         |
     into block! [
        (print "Your rules here I guess...")
     ]
] else [
    fail "Whatever"
]
</code></pre>
<p>This is just a high-level thought of pushing down the higher level matching tasks into UPARSE instead of keeping it fully separate.  If your input was calculated, you could still call it up with <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> ... although that wouldn't be available to the GROUP! code.</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; uparse-value 1 + 2 [integer! (print "int") &lt;input&gt; | text! (print "text", #text)]
int
== 3

&gt;&gt; uparse-value "foo" [integer! (print "int") &lt;input&gt; | text! (print "text", #text)]
text
== #text
</code></pre>
<p>But you're no worse off than in a switch statement that doesn't have calculated input captured under a name.  (Slightly better, in fact, since you have a means of calling up the calculated input.)</p>
<p>It's just a thought, because I've seen this pattern several times: "I have a decision tree but I can't start doing parsing until I have a series".  This is just an idea about stretching all the matching and extraction logic that is going to be needed in UPARSE anyway to apply to single values.</p>
<h2>UPARSE-VALUE or UPARSE/VALUE</h2>
<p>This strongly parallels the LOAD-VALUE vs. LOAD issue.  It seemed to make more sense in that case to separate it out so LOAD was fully generic and unconcerned with the /VALUE aspect.  This might or might not have the same rationale as to why UPARSE shouldn't internally be concerned with the behavior.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/contemplating-uparse-value/1822">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/contemplating-uparse-value/1822</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 08:43:30 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1822</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/contemplating-uparse-value/1822.rss">Contemplating UPARSE-VALUE</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>What Should BLANK! in UPARSE Do?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Parsing</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>It's always good to look at history first.  So let's compare and contrast #[none] vs. empty block in old Redbols.</p>
<p><strong>In Rebol2 and R3-Alpha, both are no-ops.</strong>  The input type doesn't matter.</p>
<pre><code>r2/r3&gt;&gt; parse {ab} [[] "a" [] "b" []]
== true

r2/r3&gt;&gt; parse {ab} [#[none] "a" #[none] "b" #[none]]
== true

r2/r3&gt;&gt; parse [a b] [[] 'a [] 'b []]
== true

r2/r3&gt;&gt; parse [a b] [#[none] 'a #[none] 'b #[none]]
== true
</code></pre>
<p><strong>In Red, #[none]s are expected to be literal.</strong>  However, you don't get an error on string inputs...just a failure.</p>
<pre><code>red&gt;&gt; parse {ab} [[] "a" [] "b" []]
== true

red&gt;&gt; parse {ab} [#[none] "a" #[none] "b" #[none]]
== false

red&gt;&gt; parse [a b] [[] 'a [] 'b []]
== true

red&gt;&gt; parse [a b] [#[none] 'a #[none] 'b #[none]]
== false

red&gt;&gt; parse [#[none] a #[none] b #[none]] [#[none] 'a #[none] 'b #[none]]
== true
</code></pre>
<h2>I Think No-Op Is the Superior Choice for BLANK! (NONE!)</h2>
<p>Ren-C's philosophy surrounding blank as "reified nothing" is that it is there to signal opting-out.</p>
<p>It's raison d'etre is being falsey, and easy to test for its nothing-ish state...easily convertible to and from NULL.  (NULL rules are errors, as they should be).</p>
<p>The idea of being able to look for literal values is being explored other ways, the @ was one proposal (though this is going back and forth).</p>
<pre><code>  &gt;&gt; var: _

  &gt;&gt; uparse [_ _ _] [some @var]
  == #[true]
</code></pre>
<p>But a blank rule is more effectively a no-op, IMO.</p>
<p>(For a time it had been considered that it could be a way of matching ANY-VALUE!, but that is now done more clearly with the <strong><code>&lt;any&gt;</code></strong> tag combinator, which is working out splendidly.)</p>
<h2>What Should a BLANK! Rule's Synthesized Product Be?</h2>
<p>When it comes to empty blocks, I'm pretty solidly sold that the answer is a ~none~ isotope:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; rule: []

&gt;&gt; did uparse {ab} ["a" x: rule "b"]
== #[true]

&gt;&gt; x
** Script Error: x is ~none~ isotope
</code></pre>
<p>There's a deeply interlocked set of justifications for that, which (I hope) aren't going to need rethinking.</p>
<p>But with BLANK! rules it's not so obvious:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; rule: _

&gt;&gt; did uparse {ab} ["a" x: rule "b"]
== #[true]

&gt;&gt; x
== ???
</code></pre>
<p>I'm skeptical of vaporization, e.g. <strong><code>(x = "b")</code></strong>  It seems that would be useful only in the most rare of situations, and 99% of the time it would surprise the caller.</p>
<p>The philosophy of "blank in, null out" suggests NULL.  That seems useful.  (Implementation of this would actually return a <em>null isotope</em>, such that the rule could still look successful while handing back that result!)</p>
<p>I think that gives a pretty interesting shape to things.  Because this is new, I'll have to look for applications of it...but I'm pretty sure they will show up.  If I see any, I'll make a note of them here.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/what-should-blank-in-uparse-do/1821">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/what-should-blank-in-uparse-do/1821</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 22:35:24 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1821</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/what-should-blank-in-uparse-do/1821.rss">What Should BLANK! in UPARSE Do?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>The Rebellion Against Style Guides</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Philosophy</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>While driving from Huntsville to Florida, I listened to a talk given by a guy who oversees the general style guide for all of Google's multi-millions of lines of C++.</p>
<p>He spoke very positively about a formatting tool called <code>clang-format</code>, and how if he had his way at Google...there would be no arguing over code formatting.  He felt the robot did a better job on average than even the best developers...and being willing to delegate formatting to the tool gave them time to work on more important things.</p>
<p><strong>My well-known opinion for code like C++ or Rust or Java is that it is best represented as a graph data structure that captures the relationships and identities.</strong>  How you render that is up to the program you use to view and edit the projection of that essential code.  It doesn't matter if code is in braces or has a box drawn around it.  You could make expressions feed into an actual logical circuit AND gate instead of using <code>&amp;&amp;</code> or the word <code>and</code> or what-have-you.</p>
<p><strong>But Rebol is different (and almost absurdist) in the software world.</strong>  If anything, it has an <em>anti</em>-style guide, in <a href="http://www.rebol.com/article/0103.html">The Deep Lake / (Swamp)</a>, where Carl says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Suppose I write:</p>
<pre><code>if time &gt; 10:00 [
    wakeup user
]
</code></pre>
<p>which some users may choose to rewrite it this way:</p>
<pre><code>if time &gt; 10:00
[
    wakeup user
    alert "Time to work"
 ]
</code></pre>
<p>But, what if the "then block" is a variable itself, defined as:</p>
<pre><code> action: [
     wakeup user
     alert "Time to work"
  ]
</code></pre>
<p>Would you write this:</p>
<pre><code>  if time &gt; 10:00
      action
</code></pre>
<p>or this:</p>
<pre><code>   if time &gt; 10:00 action
</code></pre>
</blockquote>
<p>The conclusion is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>...<strong>how you write code is ultimately your choice alone</strong>. REBOL, as a context dependent language, is perhaps the most freeform computing language ever invented.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm bringing this up because I'm mothballing an old Trello and looking for any links or information worth preserving.  It had a card requesting a style guide, pointing out a limited bit that had been written in the Rebol2 manual:</p>
<p><a href="http://www.rebol.com/docs/core23/rebolcore-5.html#section-5">http://www.rebol.com/docs/core23/rebolcore-5.html#section-5</a></p>
<p>I'm really only interested in the bits that reduce complexity (like just-say-no-to-CRLF files, or tabs, etc.)  As for the code itself, this is kind of an ASCII-art medium.</p>
<p>So a good "style guide" for Rebol would be one that showed examples of how to take advantage of the degrees of freedom to be bent to your purposes.  I think a good one was the <strong><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/testing-generic-tuple-and-path-structuring/1353">tuple and path test dialect</a></strong>.  But there are certainly more!</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/the-rebellion-against-style-guides/1819">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/the-rebellion-against-style-guides/1819</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 05:39:18 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1819</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/the-rebellion-against-style-guides/1819.rss">The Rebellion Against Style Guides</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>`greb` : Grep Using PARSE?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>System Tools</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>There was a Trello card with a remark from <a class="mention" href="/u/johnk">@johnk</a> about an idea from Pekr:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Not sure how this would work, but it is an interesting excercise to think about.  Something that bridges between unix and rebol syntax like:</p>
<pre><code>ls | greb 'some alpha ".reb"'
</code></pre>
<p>(assuming a few more built in rules/charsets)</p>
<p>May need a collect/keep kind of wrapper to retrieve data cleanly.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This would be a very small subset of what <a class="mention" href="/u/blackattr">@BlackATTR</a>'s QUERY could do...but it seems like it wouldn't hurt if we went ahead and made this program as a test and put it in the <a href="https://github.com/metaeducation/ren-c-stdio">ren-c-stdio</a> repository.</p>
<p>I've already made things like TAC (backwards unix CAT), where the goal is to see how essential and correct we can make things:</p>
<aside class="onebox githubblob">
  <header class="source">
      <a href="https://github.com/metaeducation/ren-c-stdio/blob/7fc17e5bb36ceeb7f688516ba57db5ad84a923c9/tests/tac.r#L19-L21" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <h4><a href="https://github.com/metaeducation/ren-c-stdio/blob/7fc17e5bb36ceeb7f688516ba57db5ad84a923c9/tests/tac.r#L19-L21" target="_blank" rel="noopener">metaeducation/ren-c-stdio/blob/7fc17e5bb36ceeb7f688516ba57db5ad84a923c9/tests/tac.r#L19-L21</a></h4>
<pre class="onebox"><code class="lang-r"><ol class="start lines" start="19" style="counter-reset: li-counter 18 ;">
<li>write-stdout try delimit/tail newline reverse collect [</li>
<li>    until [not keep line: try read-line]</li>
<li>]</li>
</ol></code></pre>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p><strong>I like the idea of making GREB similarly essential, and part of the samples.</strong>  Worth doing.</p>
<p>(Note that <code>grep</code> was itself originally framed as a one-line <code>awk</code> program.)</p>
<p>I'll also throw in a little ping that it would be nice to have a simple web app that exposed PARSE functionality with some highlighting, like <a href="http://regexpal.com/">http://regexpal.com/</a>.  Seems sometimes we get such big ideas in our head we forget to do the small ones (!)</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/greb-grep-using-parse/1818">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/greb-grep-using-parse/1818</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 05:09:22 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1818</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/greb-grep-using-parse/1818.rss">`greb` : Grep Using PARSE?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Mustache Templates vs RSP</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Web</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>On an old Trello I found a link to this renderer for "Mustache":</p>
<aside class="onebox githubfolder">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://github.githubassets.com/favicons/favicon.svg" class="site-icon" width="16" height="16">
      <a href="https://github.com/kronwiz/r3-mustache" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img src="https://opengraph.githubassets.com/1e73d9d2c54389cdd35bded29734b54c3d25b8293c427a9df0cc11db00084d73/kronwiz/r3-mustache" class="thumbnail onebox-full-image" width="60" height="60">

<h3><a href="https://github.com/kronwiz/r3-mustache" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub - kronwiz/r3-mustache: Mustache templates renderer for Rebol 3</a></h3>


  <p><span class="label1">Mustache templates renderer for Rebol 3. Contribute to kronwiz/r3-mustache development by creating an account on GitHub.</span></p>

  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>It may or may not be interesting.  <a class="mention" href="/u/rgchris">@rgchris</a> said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"I'd suggest looking at my <a href="http://reb4.me/r3/rsp">RSP engine</a> for handling string templates, local values, sanitization. LOAD-RSP loads a template and returns a function. That function can be applied to a block of local words and returns a completed string. The template need only be loaded once."*</p>
</blockquote>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/mustache-templates-vs-rsp/1817">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/mustache-templates-vs-rsp/1817</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 04:56:01 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1817</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/mustache-templates-vs-rsp/1817.rss">Mustache Templates vs RSP</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>(U)PARSE + CALL: Controlling Of Interactive CLI Apps</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>General Tools</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>A long time ago (e.g. college), I used something in Tcl called EXPECT...which was a great way of driving interactive console applications.</p>
<p>You'd specify the patterns you wanted to wait on (that came from the app's stdout), and script the responses to be fed to stdin, in an interactive fashion.</p>
<p>Today people think a lot more about exposing functionality through APIs (with whatever Java or XML and such).  So it's more rare that you have to resort to writing "stdio robots".</p>
<p>But it's a pretty easy-to-absorb test case, and could be a real showcase for UPARSE...as well as a good challenge for a renewed PORT! model.</p>
<p>I found this code from <a class="mention" href="/u/brett">@Brett</a> on Trello, where the need for an R3 version of CALL was being articulated.  It gives some EXPECT-like functionality:</p>
<aside class="onebox githubblob">
  <header class="source">
      <a href="https://github.com/codebybrett/r3-scripts/blob/master/call-server.r" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <h4><a href="https://github.com/codebybrett/r3-scripts/blob/master/call-server.r" target="_blank" rel="noopener">codebybrett/r3-scripts/blob/master/call-server.r</a></h4>
<pre><code class="lang-r">REBOL [
	Title: "call-server"
	File: %call-server.r
	Author: "Brett Handley"
	Date: 22-Jun-2013
	Purpose: "Provides a way to capture output from console program and send input to interactive console programs."
	License: {

		Copyright 2013 Brett Handley

		Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
		you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
		You may obtain a copy of the License at

			http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

		Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
		distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
		WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
		See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
</code></pre>

  This file has been truncated. <a href="https://github.com/codebybrett/r3-scripts/blob/master/call-server.r" target="_blank" rel="noopener">show original</a>

  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>This seems like a good domain to build some simple-but-impressive demos for... in the "layperson could have built this robot" sense (if we can push it to that point).</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/u-parse-call-controlling-of-interactive-cli-apps/1816">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/u-parse-call-controlling-of-interactive-cli-apps/1816</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 04:52:57 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1816</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/u-parse-call-controlling-of-interactive-cli-apps/1816.rss">(U)PARSE + CALL: Controlling Of Interactive CLI Apps</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Hex-Valued Integer Literals: Likely Not In Ren-C</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Datatypes</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>On an old Trello there was a card about standardizing the differences between R3-Alpha and Red...and a checklist with only one item:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Hex-valued literal notation (Rebol has none, Red used to use FFh, FFFFh, FFFFFFFFh), now using 0#FF</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The motivation was for purposes of Red/System, mostly.</p>
<p>In Ren-C this doesn't seem like a priority.  It has ISSUE! (TOKEN!) as a read-only data type that fits in a cell.  Hence a systems-oriented dialect already has an efficient way to represent these values.</p>
<p>For instance: it's not a big deal if your assembler says <strong>[mov ax, <span class="hashtag">#FE</span>]</strong> in its source... if it's generating machine code.</p>
<p>Of course, an ISSUE! in it isn't the same from a metaprogramming sense as a slot with an INTEGER! in it.  So you don't get the automatic advantage of <em>every</em> dialect that has INTEGER! support for a given slot working with a hex notation.  But isn't that what COMPOSE is for...?</p>
<pre><code>my-dialect [something-or-another 255]

my-dialect compose [whatever (debin [BE +] #FF)]
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Having more than one representation for the same type is generally bad, anyway.</strong>  Let's look at what Red does here:</p>
<pre><code>red&gt;&gt; FFh
== 255

red&gt;&gt; F0h + 0Fh
== 255
</code></pre>
<p>If it was so important that it had to be encoded in source, why is it thrown away immediately?</p>
<p>It's something about Red worth knowing exists, but off the radar for implementing, methinks.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/hex-valued-integer-literals-likely-not-in-ren-c/1815">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/hex-valued-integer-literals-likely-not-in-ren-c/1815</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 04:35:56 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1815</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/hex-valued-integer-literals-likely-not-in-ren-c/1815.rss">Hex-Valued Integer Literals: Likely Not In Ren-C</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Old Idea from DocKimbel For Rebol2 =&gt; Rebol3/Red</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Redbol</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>This is something I just ran across from a long time ago, which I thought would be interesting to look at with modern eyes.</p>
<p>It's a Gist: <a href="https://gist.github.com/dockimbel/5083375">https://gist.github.com/dockimbel/5083375</a> of a proposal of actually making a DO variant that would rewrite the source of a script.</p>
<p>He is quoted as having said: <em>"A JIT-migration tool would be more accurate. It would run just after LOAD and before DO to rewrite part of the R2 sources in a R3 compatible format."</em></p>
<p>Static analysis of Turing-Complete programs is notoriously on the difficult-if-not-impossible scale, even for simple languages.  So JIT-rewriting even something like PARSE rules is only going to be feasible if those rules were not built by code.</p>
<p>His example just looks for one source pattern (negative literal indexing, so like translating between <strong><code>data/0</code></strong> and <strong><code>data/-1</code></strong>).  But determining what is "code" and what is "data" is deliberately more complex in Rebol than other language.</p>
<p>In Ren-C we have code like <code>enbin [BE +/- 32]</code> and that path is never meant to execute, it's just there to convey the notion of wanting to encode a signed number.  Going around and randomly turning all paths with 0 in them to be -1 misses the whole point of "relative expressions"; you don't know what they're relative to.</p>
<p>So the ironic point of preserving this is just to say "nothing to see, here".  <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=9" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:">  <code>%redbol.reb</code> is a saner track.  But I do think it's going to wind up requiring DO itself being different... a DO2 (like UPARSE2).  It won't rewriting the code block given, but hook the evaluator with different rules.</p>
<pre><code>REBOL [
    Author:  "Nenad Rakocevic"
    Date:      04/03/2013
    Purpose: {
        Show how to achieve R2 source rewriting suitable for evaluation
        using R3 interpreter.
    }
        Note: "Use it from %Red/ folder"
]

context [
    do*: s: none
    
    path-rewrite: [
        some [
            s: integer! (if negative? s/1 [s/1: s/1 + 1])
            ;| handle other indexed-access cases here
            | skip
        ]
    ]

    patched-do: func [value /arg /local saved rule mark path file][
        unless file? :value [return do* value]

        saved: system/script/path
        set [path file] split-path :value
        change-dir path
        value: load file

        parse value rule: [
            any [
                mark: [path! | set-path! | lit-path!] :mark into path-rewrite
                ;; | mark: string! :mark into string-rewrite 
                ;; add more rewritting rules here
                | mark: any-block! :mark into rule
                | skip
            ]
        ]
        also 
            do* value
            system/script/path: saved
    ]
    
    set 'do-r2 func [blk [block!]][
        do*: :do
        set 'do :patched-do
        do blk
        set 'do :do*
    ]
]

do-r2 [
    do %red/compiler.r
]
save %red.new red  ;-- inspect the file to see the changes
halt</code></pre>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/old-idea-from-dockimbel-for-rebol2-rebol3-red/1814">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/old-idea-from-dockimbel-for-rebol2-rebol3-red/1814</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 04:12:29 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1814</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/old-idea-from-dockimbel-for-rebol2-rebol3-red/1814.rss">Old Idea from DocKimbel For Rebol2 =&gt; Rebol3/Red</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Is GROUP! in PATH! for function invocations worth it?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Internals</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Back in the day, I thought it would be neat to allow you to put GROUP!s in paths.  So you could do things like this:</p>
<pre><code>append/(if condition ['only]) [a b c] [d e]
</code></pre>
<p>It turned out to be of fairly limited use.  Really you could only use it with refinements that didn't take parameters, because it changes the "shape" of the execution stream.  Consider how you would make the following sensible:</p>
<pre><code>append/(if condition ['dup]) [a b c] [d e] ???
</code></pre>
<p>When the condition is true you want something in the ??? spot.  When it's false you don't.  How can your code cover both cases?</p>
<p><em>We actually have some tools these days</em> that could use opportunistic invisibility to solve this.  But then you're testing the condition twice, and getting involved in some pretty wild mechanics for something trivial.</p>
<p>It also raised a lot of annoying questions about NULL/blank tolerance.  I didn't like NULL being allowed in the generic pathing, but it was ugly to require BLANK! for this task:</p>
<pre><code>append/(try if condition ['only]) [a b c] [d e]

append/(if condition ['only] else [_]) [a b c] [d e]
</code></pre>
<h2><strong><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/apply-ii-the-revenge/1406/3">Now we have a modern APPLY</a></strong></h2>
<p>It bends some of the raw frame rules, and lets you use LOGIC! for parameterless refinements:</p>
<pre><code>apply :append [[a b c] [d e] /only condition]
</code></pre>
<p>It's a bit longer.  And we haven't really firmed up questions like whether you need the GET-WORD! or if it's soft quoted by default.  Or if there might be some clever shorthand:</p>
<pre><code>($ append [a b c] [d e] /only condition)
</code></pre>
<h2>I'm In A Mood To Kill Off Lesser-Loved Features <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/hocho.png?v=9" title=":hocho:" class="emoji" alt=":hocho:">
</h2>
<p>All things being equal, it might seem nice to support.  But every feature has a cost!</p>
<p><strong>You'd still be able to put GROUP!s in paths for your own purposes, but refinement dispatch in functions wouldn't use it.</strong></p>
<p>You could also use DO of COMPOSE'd code if you really wanted to:</p>
<pre><code>do compose/deep [
    append/(if condition ['only]) [a b c] [d e]
]
</code></pre>
<p>So if anyone has a good argument for keeping the function dispatch behavior, speak up now!</p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/is-group-in-path-for-function-invocations-worth-it/1813">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/is-group-in-path-for-function-invocations-worth-it/1813</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 04:35:59 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1813</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/is-group-in-path-for-function-invocations-worth-it/1813.rss">Is GROUP! in PATH! for function invocations worth it?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Asymmetric Encryption/Decryption in Ren-C</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Cryptography</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>The most easily recognized form of encryption is symmetric, where the same password is used to encrypt something as to decrypt it.</p>
<p>But a weirder form is <strong>asymmetric encryption</strong>, <em>where the key used to encrypt is different from the one used to decrypt</em>.</p>
<h2>Ren-C Supports RSA Public/Private Encryption</h2>
<p>You generate your keys in a pair, which come back via multiple return results.  You must specify a size for the public key (in <em>bits</em>, not <em>bytes</em>...<a href="https://crypto.stackexchange.com/questions/58124/">because that's the convention</a>)</p>
<p>We'll start using [raw] RSA encryption:</p>
<pre><code>; use /INSECURE to override errors that tell you the key is too small
; (makes examples more readable)

&gt;&gt; [public-key private-key]: rsa-generate-keypair/padding/insecure 128 [raw]
== make object! [
    padding: [raw]
    n: #{C097238C34E7191561DD7D30BBB77C65}
    e: #{010001}
]

&gt;&gt; length of public-key.n
== 16  ; 16 bytes is 128 bits
</code></pre>
<p>When you use raw mode encryption, the data you encrypt must be <em>exactly the same size</em> as the key you made.  We'll show how to work around this later, but for now let's just deal with it.</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; data: #{0123456789ABCDEFFEDCBA9876543210}

&gt;&gt; length of data
== 16  ; same size as our key

&gt;&gt; encrypted: rsa-encrypt data public-key
== #{3F7E8ACD2DEE61D09B7A6FC914E22295}

&gt;&gt; length of encrypted
== 16  ; also same length as key
</code></pre>
<p>Now, decryption is done with the private key:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; rsa-decrypt encrypted private-key
== #{0123456789ABCDEFFEDCBA9876543210}
</code></pre>
<h2>But <code>[raw]</code> Makes The Same Message Every Time...</h2>
<p>Raw RSA doesn't waste any space (e.g. 4096 bytes in means 4096 bytes out).  <strong>But a given output always produces the same output with raw RSA</strong>:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; rsa-encrypt data public-key
== #{3F7E8ACD2DEE61D09B7A6FC914E22295}

&gt;&gt; rsa-encrypt data public-key
== #{3F7E8ACD2DEE61D09B7A6FC914E22295}
</code></pre>
<p>This can make it easy (or at least, easier) for someone who doesn't have the private key to do some factoring with the public key, and see if they can generate input that produces that output...effectively defeating the encryption.</p>
<p>Also since it requires exactly the keysize of data coming in, you're likely going to have a lot of cases where you have to throw in some padding.  But naive answers to padding also create security problems:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>It would be bad to pad the data block with zeros (or whatever)</strong>, because such predictable behavior generally makes it easier to guess what the encrypted information might be.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>It would be bad to just put random data in the padding</strong>, because the person doing the decryption wouldn't know if the gibberish they got when decrypting was the same gibberish you put in.</p>
<ul>
<li>Attackers could leverage this random tolerance to forge data in the non-padded portions, then forging the padding in a way that compensated.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><a href="https://security.stackexchange.com/a/183330">Real-World problems motivated the tricks that are used to resist attacks.</a></strong>  You can read about them if you want...or just don't use <code>[raw]</code> and you'll get a sensible default.</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; [public-a private-a]: rsa-generate-keypair/insecure 128
== make object! [
    padding: [pkcs1-v15]
    n: #{A9EE9282744CC0FC6765824EB2B87539}
    e: #{010001}
]

&gt;&gt; one: rsa-encrypt #{DECAFBAD} public-a  ; Note: shorter input than key
== #{13C14811A3B1CD95100BA4F3273F0962}

&gt;&gt; two: rsa-encrypt #{DECAFBAD} public-a
== #{3245179A18C6B488FD39CDE7B4F5E3EC}  ; different!

&gt;&gt; rsa-decrypt one private-a
== #{DECAFBAD}

&gt;&gt; rsa-decrypt two private-a
== #{DECAFBAD}
</code></pre>
<h2>That Encrypts Smaller Than The Key...But What About Bigger?</h2>
<p>A fundamental issue with RSA encryption/decryption is it is relatively S-L-O-W.  And if you want to futureproof a key to use with big file sizes, those keys would also be B-I-G!</p>
<p><strong>But you can use a smaller asymmetric key as a stepping stone to providing a symmetric key.</strong></p>
<p>It's easy!  Let's say someone has published their 4096-bit public key and you want to send them a 100 megabyte file that only they will know how to open.  Follow these steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Generate a random string that's less than 4096 bits, and encrypt <em>that</em> with their public key</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Encrypt the file using a faster symmetric algorithm, with that random string as the password</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Send the recipient both the asymmetrically-encrypted random string and the symmetrically-encrypted 100mb file</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Your recipient uses their private key to decrypt the one-off password you randomly generated, and decrypts the symmetrically encrypted file with it.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2>It's All New, So Help Design the Interface...</h2>
<p>The original motivation to research mbedTLS was so that <a class="mention" href="/u/gchiu">@gchiu</a> didn't have to call out to external utilities to generate RSA keys.</p>
<p>But the generation abilities weren't actually written until now.  And honestly, I'm not sure the RSA stuff was even working at all.  :-/  <strong><a href="https://github.com/metaeducation/ren-c/blob/master/extensions/crypt/tests/rsa.test.reb">Now there's at least a minimal amount of testing.</a></strong></p>
<p>I think the multiple return values are a good start on making it clear, but it's certainly a good time for feedback if anyone has any.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/asymmetric-encryption-decryption-in-ren-c/1812">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/asymmetric-encryption-decryption-in-ren-c/1812</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2022 01:17:30 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1812</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/asymmetric-encryption-decryption-in-ren-c/1812.rss">Asymmetric Encryption/Decryption in Ren-C</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Transitioning from mbedTLS 2 to mbedTLS 3: Promise and Peril</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Cryptography</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Historically R3-Alpha had its few pieces of crypto math cobbled together from generally unknown sources on the Internet...</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>My understanding is that Rebol2's support for talking to a limited set of HTTPS sites was written entirely in C.  It's never been open-sourced, so we don't know much about it--such as whether it was original code or done with some early TLS library of the time.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Saphirion chose to split out the code for the Transport-Layer-Security protocol and make it usermode Rebol.  Only the foundational cryptographic primitives like <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/checksums-and-secure-hashes-in-ren-c/1808">Secure Hashes</a> or <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/key-exchange-methods-in-ren-c/1809">Key Exchange</a> were written in C.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Many of R3-Alpha's C cryptography bits seemed to come from the (one-man?) effort known as <a href="http://axtls.sourceforge.net/">Axolotl TLS (AxTLS)</a></strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Rebol parts were written by Cyphre (Richard Smolak)</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2>I Was Initially Very Skeptical of Continuing Saphirion's Strategy...</h2>
<p>If a change ever rippled into affecting the TLS file, it was a voodoo nightmare to figure out how to fix it.  I didn't understand why limited efforts should be stretched into involvement with "something the language wasn't really good for".</p>
<p><em>My impression was also that the %prot-tls.r implementation was bad.</em>  But when I got to looking at the details, the most insidious problems weren't so much the fault of the protocol code.  It more-or-less followed the spec, in a pretty literate way (that I <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/dissecting-the-tls-emit-dialect/1498">improved with some dialecting</a>).</p>
<p>The main frustrations regarding prot-tls came from the fact that <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/the-weirdness-of-wait/1703">R3-Alpha's asynchronous port model made no sense</a>.  When I rewrote it to use the "seemingly-synchronous" model (which aims to parallel the Go language), it became more clear.</p>
<p><strong>Through the process of implementing TLS 1.2, I began to get the impression that such protocols may actually be a fitting domain for a language like Rebol.</strong></p>
<p>Today's %prot-tls.r is an aggressive and practical test of dialecting.  If it continues to be enhanced may be a case of exposing the workings of an important protocol to the layperson.</p>
<h2>We Needed More Cryptography, and mbedTLS Fit the Bill</h2>
<p>Adding TLS 1.2 wasn't going to do any good without also providing some of the newer exotic cipher suites that are demanded these days.  That meant getting things like elliptic curve key exchange, or SHA512, or anything else the future may demand.</p>
<p>When I found mbedTLS it was much "cleaner" than OpenSSL, and seemed perfect:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>It was targeting embedded processors, with <a href="https://github.com/Mbed-TLS/mbedtls/blob/42650260a9109f53d2058f82e1133205545fd65b/include/mbedtls/mbedtls_config.h">incredibly granular controls</a> for doing things like using smaller/slower algorithms vs. bigger/faster ones.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Pure C code, that could be compiled even by TCC.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>This meant the conference demo of bootstrap could still work, with a TCC-built R3-WITH-TCC having enough cryptography in it to download its own source from an HTTPS GitHub link.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>The cryptography primitives could be lifted out "a la carte" from the C-based TLS protocol code; the files seemed completely separate:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>If we wanted to, we could have a C-based mbedTLS extension option instead of using %prot-tls.r, and it could reuse the same cryptography.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>(We may at some point have to resort to this, if keeping %prot-tls.r up to date with the times proves impractical.)</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>The interfaces for every cipher and hash supported streaming, so we'd have the ability to incrementally do cryptography on large files or network connections (assuming we figured out how to expose that).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>And critically, all of it was under the umbrella of a working group at ARM which would hopefully ensure that it was kept up to date, and being vetted for problems.</strong></p>
<p>All of it made this seem like a no-brainer to build on, which <a href="https://github.com/metaeducation/ren-c/commit/06e110235efb68500700fead3478a3216899d780">I did in April of 2020</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The mbedTLS library is an embedded-focused set of cryptography hashes,<br>
key exchanges, block ciphers, and other tools.  Its components range<br>
from lower-level facilities like BigNum arithmetic, to higher-level<br>
services like TLS negotiation and certificate validation.  Its<br>
facilities are well-factored such that each piece can be used with only<br>
its dependencies:</p>
<p><a href="https://tls.mbed.org/">https://tls.mbed.org/</a></p>
<p>Because of its fine-grained control, it's possible to use its basic<br>
tools while still keeping higher-level negotiations as spec-driven<br>
usermode Rebol (e.g. the TLS protocol itself) to facilitate more<br>
hooking and understanding.  And because it offers a consistent set of<br>
vetted and active code, it can replace the "hodgepodge" of cut-and-paste<br>
snippets for cryptography (originating from axTLS, internet sources,<br>
custom code, edited OpenSSL, etc.) where there are problems like not<br>
being written to a common BigNum implementation.</p>
<p>Additionally--due to the factoring, it is hoped that this code could be<br>
used as the basis for implementing BigNum arithmetic in the interpreter<br>
core itself...which would be naturally reused in the implementation<br>
of these C algorithms when cryptographic extensions are loaded.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Possibly inspired by this--or just his own coming to the same conclusions--<a href="https://github.com/Oldes/Rebol3/commit/77515519655a579fbef99f7e185a27a4451718d7">Oldes changed his hashes to use mbedTLS in January 2021</a></p>
<h2>...and Then, Version 3.0 Came... <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/dragon.png?v=9" title=":dragon:" class="emoji" alt=":dragon:">
</h2>
<p><em>I probably should have been paying more attention to what mbedTLS was planning in their future branches.</em></p>
<p>What I've gathered is that ARM (or someone) was pointing out that mbedTLS not only needed to implement TLS 1.3, but that it wasn't sufficiently fast vs. the competition.</p>
<p>A somewhat-sensible approach to optimization is to first tighten the control over your data structures, making them more opaque to clients.  By limiting the APIs you can use to access those structures, you can know more about the states they are in...and take more for granted.  Your functions can then make optimizations which leverage these rules--adding or rearranging fields in more clever ways.</p>
<p><strong>But I didn't want cleverness, I just wanted the math.</strong>  I liked that our objects for things like Diffie-Hellman showed you the true cryptographic parameters, and wasn't some kind of "black box".  If we were closed off from that, everything would be a HANDLE! and you would have limited ways of extracting parameters from it.</p>
<p>Not only did they close off access to the structure members, many APIs they offered were TLS-specific!</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>If a cryptographic primitive depended on parameters X and Y and produced Z, they'd offer a function that takes in a blob of data representing X and Y <em>in the specific format that TLS messages encode them</em>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If you were building some protocol that <em>wasn't</em> TLS using that basic crypto primitive, the only way offered to load the parameters was to make a TLS-format message buffer and pass it.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The TLS-specific functions were creeping into what were supposed to be the "a la carte" cryptography files, adding bloat at compile time (if not also runtime) if you weren't using them.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>One can imagine that this seems good from the point of view of speeding up their C TLS protocol, but bad for anyone trying to use the underlying cryptography.</p>
<p>There was an announcement I missed that it would be split into two libraries: "mbed crypto" and "mbedTLS", to serve the two different audiences for the code.  But that seemed to be short-lived, and "mbed crypto" was reabsorbed into the mbedTLS codebase.  Not before the damage had been done to the layering and generality.</p>
<p>So now mbedTLS seems to be playing catch-up on serving the audience that wanted the crypto primitives.  But functionality that had an endorsed method to do in mbedTLS 2 now requires hacking beneath the approved API to accomplish.</p>
<h2>On the bright side...</h2>
<p>Since the re-absorption of "mbed crypto", mbedTLS seems amenable to having answers for the a-la-carte crypto crowd.  <a href="https://github.com/Mbed-TLS/mbedtls/issues/5818">A request I made is at least marked medium importance</a>.</p>
<p>Also, the API becoming more formalized is pointing out some weird mistakes that were made before in the code...filling structure parameters that were unused, for instance.  Having to call each of these things into question is a good vetting of the code.</p>
<p>And although I had to use hacks to do it, we now can run https on top of mbedTLS 3.  I've been a little on the fence of whether to stick with mbedTLS 2 (support ending in 2024) or find some other library.  But writing about cryptography has made me realize it's a bit of a red herring on the importance scale, and I think we're better off rolling with the punches of mbedTLS 3 than going it some other route.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/transitioning-from-mbedtls-2-to-mbedtls-3-promise-and-peril/1810">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/transitioning-from-mbedtls-2-to-mbedtls-3-promise-and-peril/1810</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 14:47:25 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1810</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/transitioning-from-mbedtls-2-to-mbedtls-3-promise-and-peril/1810.rss">Transitioning from mbedTLS 2 to mbedTLS 3: Promise and Peril</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Key Exchange Methods in Ren-C</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Cryptography</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Having given a summary of <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/checksums-and-secure-hashes-in-ren-c/1808/">Checksums and Secure Hashes</a>, I thought I'd follow up with a quick description of something you're likely not as familiar with: <strong>Key Exchanges</strong>.</p>
<p>There's old quote I like (but can't find a source for):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The shared secret is capital.  We may spend it or squander it."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>An example of taking advantage of a shared secret is when people want to share an encrypted .ZIP file.  If you and your friend both know the encryption password that no one else knows...then you could put the file on a public server for your friend to download.  If you trust the encryption, the fact it was public would not matter.</p>
<p><strong>But what if the situation is that your friend has a password that only they know... and you have a password that only you know?</strong>  That wouldn't seem to help with the .ZIP file scenario, because it expects the same password to decrypt as was used to encrypt it.</p>
<p>Key Exchange is a way of taking your individual "passwords" and coming to an agreement on a third "password" that only the two of you know.  Amazingly enough, you can carry out the conversation where you establish the shared password in public.</p>
<h2>Creating one Shared Secret from two Non-Shared Secrets</h2>
<p>For educational purposes, people use paint-mixing as an analogy for key exchange.  It's really "multiplying big prime numbers" instead of mixing paint, but it's visual and easy to see.</p>
<p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/original/1X/184fa9035c24ffa1250e324b61acaa3915f7757e.png" data-download-href="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/184fa9035c24ffa1250e324b61acaa3915f7757e" title="image"><img src="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/184fa9035c24ffa1250e324b61acaa3915f7757e_2_345x500.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="3t485Do7kYfAw6HMsMv5klePtsq" width="345" height="500" srcset="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/184fa9035c24ffa1250e324b61acaa3915f7757e_2_345x500.png, https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/original/1X/184fa9035c24ffa1250e324b61acaa3915f7757e.png 1.5x, https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/original/1X/184fa9035c24ffa1250e324b61acaa3915f7757e.png 2x" data-small-upload="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/184fa9035c24ffa1250e324b61acaa3915f7757e_2_10x10.png"><div class="meta">
<svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-far-image svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#far-image"></use></svg><span class="filename">image</span><span class="informations">480695 28 KB</span><svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-discourse-expand svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#discourse-expand"></use></svg>
</div></a></div></p>
<p>This assumes everyone in the world has some kind of weird "common paint".  This paint isn't white (because if you mixed it with something that would be too easy to guess at the precise shade you had mixed it with).  And it isn't black (because mixing might just get you something too dark to measure well).</p>
<p>But the key point to absorb is what the diagram says: <strong>we assume that mixture separation is expensive</strong>.  Once you've mixed the common paint with your secret color, it produces a new shade that no one else knows how to make exactly.</p>
<p>When you and your friend exchange your mixtures you cleverly go to your private lairs and each add your secret color to the other's mixture.  <strong>Now both of you have the same weird color, and this is a secret you share.</strong></p>
<h2>Ren-C Supports Diffie-Hellman Key Exchange</h2>
<p>I oversimplified this by saying you each start with a "password"...because that made it sound like you could just pick a phrase out of your head.  In reality, choosing your secret involves some tricky math...to make sure your secret paint color is a <em>good</em> secret paint color.  You don't pick these--you ask the computer to generate it.</p>
<p>To get the ball rolling, you need to specify what kind of "common paint" to use.  You make that by picking two suitable prime numbers, a modulus and a base.  Then you can ask for a unique random secret to be generated.</p>
<p>For the sake of education, I've made it possible to use <em>relatively bad</em> paint mixes with the /INSECURE refinement.  It won't allow numbers that are so broken the process won't work (for instance: non-primes, or primes that don't meet the basic requirements of the algorithm).  This lets you work with small enough numbers that you can see for yourself what's going on more easily.</p>
<p>So let's use a modulus of 9 and a base of 3:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; mine: dh-generate-keypair/insecure #{09} #{05}
== make object! [
    modulus: #{09}
    generator: #{05}
    private-key: #{07}
    public-key: #{05}
]

&gt;&gt; theirs: dh-generate-keypair/insecure #{09} #{05}
== make object! [
    modulus: #{09}
    generator: #{05}
    private-key: #{05}
    public-key: #{02}
]
</code></pre>
<p>So privately, my secret is 7... and their secret is 5.  But we want to come to an agreement on a new number while only sharing with the public my "mixture" of 5 and their mixture of 2.</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; my-shared: dh-compute-secret mine theirs.public-key
== #{02}

&gt;&gt; their-shared: dh-compute-secret theirs mine.public-key
== #{02}
</code></pre>
<p>So here you see each of us could come to a common agreement of 2.  You can follow through the math on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diffie%E2%80%93Hellman_key_exchange">Wikipedia page</a> if you want...but it's enough to know that it works.</p>
<p>What makes for a good (big!) modulus and base to use?  You don't really need to come up with them yourself, although <a href="https://security.stackexchange.com/a/103924">there are algorithms for it</a>.  There are papers that publish some good choices--and we should probably provide a way to default to well-known ones, like maybe accept either an object or an ISSUE!</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; dh-generate-keypair #RFC-3526
; ...or...
&gt;&gt; dh-generate-keypair make object [base: ..., modulus: ...]
</code></pre>
<p>But the main thing to know is that <strong>both sides have to agree on the "common paint" to use</strong>, in order to come to the same conclusion.  So <code>dh-compute-secret</code> won't work unless the same numbers were used here.</p>
<h2>We Also Support Elliptic Curve Key Exchange (ECHDE)</h2>
<p>Modern Internet Transport Security has moved on from traditional Diffie Hellman to trickier math.  But the premise is the same.</p>
<p>In the interface, we only support two "common paints" for this method: "secp256r1" and "curve25519".  There's no option for small answers here:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; mine: ecc-generate-keypair 'curve25519
== make object! [
    public-key: make object! [
        x: #{121413C34DC265025F24CBEBBA6065B9
             75F1BFA6E493D07A0F4776FAE03DC245}
        y: #{00000000000000000000000000000000
             00000000000000000000000000000000}
    ]
    private-key: #{610A8D99A72500B3A2E8A1FD714FA412
                   17F0A0EA5EDFC9CFBDAE0425E199DC70}
]

&gt;&gt; theirs: ecc-generate-keypair 'curve25519
== make object! [
    public-key: make object! [
        x: #{10D65366D8C9229591C99903D3B5EB0F
             57709AD27E37989E4782050D2B9B2B93}
        y: #{00000000000000000000000000000000
             00000000000000000000000000000000}
    ]
    private-key: #{7C3262BF6028B049EEDC6C37E37A8261
                   EA4DF31F16E4D534D92A7EF11D974618}
]
</code></pre>
<p>But it works the same way; you come to the same conclusion when combining your partner's public portion with your private portion:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; my-secret: (
    ecdh-shared-secret 'curve25519 mine.private-key theirs.public-key
)
== #{E27891074A60250580B8F2C7CB2448A9AA491C97161D7C8D381348D90E438025}

&gt;&gt; their-secret: (
    ecdh-shared-secret 'curve25519 mine.private-key theirs.public-key
)
== #{E27891074A60250580B8F2C7CB2448A9AA491C97161D7C8D381348D90E438025}

&gt;&gt; my-secret = their-secret
== #[true]
</code></pre>
<h2>Would Average Users Ever Need Key Exchange Functions?</h2>
<p>Right now, the main reason most people would care whether the language has these key exchanges is because without them you can't do TLS.  So no reading or writing over HTTPS.</p>
<p>You really only need key exchanges when protocols are trying to establish private channels of communication.  So notably, some cryptographic protocols (like Bitcoin) don't need key exchanges...because they're carrying out their work in public.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>It would be neat if we could democratize the creation of cryptographic protocols</strong>.  I think giving people easier and more transparent access to these kinds of things could foster some grassroots innovation, where people would build <em>exactly the security they needed</em> into a program's design...no more and no less.</p>
<ul>
<li>This would stand in contrast to today's methods, where "security" is accomplished by standing on top of a mountain of protocols (using a literal zoo of cryptographic algorithms) to tunnel and log in somewhere that they are "safe"...and putting more data than they need to in that place.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>But even "simple" cryptography is tricky to reason about, and people are lazy.</strong>  I myself am pretty guilty of doing things like falling back on my GitHub password and resetting my keys instead of doing a good job of filing them in safe places.</p>
<ul>
<li>Convincing people their programs should be "organic and locally sourced"... by tailor-making the protocols and asking their users to keep track of files, is going to be a hard sell to those who are happy to use OAuth and leave this all up to Google.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>So pessimistically speaking, I don't know that we're going to be able to market easy-to-use key exchange to anyone as a killer feature.  It's a nice thought, and I certainly like having it available to tinker with.  But I'd be surprised if anyone reading this has an idea how to use it in something they're working on.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/key-exchange-methods-in-ren-c/1809">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/key-exchange-methods-in-ren-c/1809</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 18:20:50 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1809</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/key-exchange-methods-in-ren-c/1809.rss">Key Exchange Methods in Ren-C</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Checksums and Secure Hashes in Ren-C</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Cryptography</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I thought I'd write up a quick post about algorithms that take in a bunch of bytes--like a BINARY!--and produce a (usually) shorter "fingerprint" of that data.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>It's not hard to make an <em>insecure</em> hash...like taking the first couple of letters of a string: <code>"DICKENS" =&gt; DI</code>.  That might be useful if you're trying to divide book authors into drawers of an old-fashioned library card catalog.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>But it's easy to find another string that would make the same "DI" fingerprint, like "DIABOLICAL" or "DIR^/FORMAT C:"</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If you were using a fingerprint to trust something was what it was supposed to be, the easiness of generating these "collisions" is a liability!! <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/skull_and_crossbones.png?v=9" title=":skull_and_crossbones:" class="emoji" alt=":skull_and_crossbones:"></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Secure hashes do complicated "one-way functions" in math to make it <em>really hard</em> on today's computers to fabricate any binary sequence--even garbage--that will give you the same fingerprint as any other input.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>You've certainly seen web pages that redirect you off to download a file, but beforehand give you some bytes of what the file should securely hash to.  <sub>(And you've probably never checked to make sure they match.)</sub></p>
<h2>If the Fingerprint is Shorter than the data, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pigeonhole_principle">COLLISIONS EXIST!</a>
</h2>
<p>You obviously can't give every 500mb file in the universe a unique fingerprint that's 32-bits, 128-bits, 512-bits, 2048-bits etc.</p>
<p>So the concept behind a secure hash is just supposed to be you can't find a collision until we're all dead and no one cares.  Less grimly: we might pair a hash with an expiration date to say not to trust a hash after a very conservative guess at how long it would take for computers to advance enough to break it.</p>
<p>When this hope falls apart (e.g. if any researcher can show two inputs that generate the same fingerprint) it's generally considered that the "secure" part of that hash is broken...for the purposes of whatever time-bubble you're living in.</p>
<h2>We Have Four Secure Hashes in the Box Right Now...</h2>
<p>It shouldn't be surprising that longer fingerprints correlate with being harder to find collisions:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; checksum/method {DICKENS} 'md5
== #{3717A787E2F16310EA51DC0308E88803}  ; considered vulnerable

&gt;&gt; checksum/method {DICKENS} 'sha1
== #{DFE5DD61B2B19C319DBC4F44328CDF8D24366F88}  ; considered vulnerable

&gt;&gt; checksum/method {DICKENS} 'sha256
== #{52A095CF1F0319EF44FF9134AAD2EF5E2BFE1A48307DCB0AD0408F1CE393C950}

&gt;&gt; checksum/method {DICKENS} 'sha512
== #{
E8DBC26DE28FAA1BC2A6A3E1BC6DD22C1ECB3FD0D5FCBBFB69BC63C6AAC6A9CE
FB76294EFFB0522D4C90A5E5829233FC5BC5B811AE6684A6EA632ECB3FF88DA1
}

&gt;&gt; checksum/method {DICKENS} 'ripemd160         ; bitcoin uses this one
== #{ADC86945BE4CEF31F0CFCAF66775E1DA5160F877}  ; ...no one knows why
</code></pre>
<p>But longer isn't <em>intrinsically</em> better...there might be a weakness to exploit in the method used by a longer hash which isn't present in shorter ones.  However, a bunch of mathematicians look at this stuff and we would generally hope that we'd be getting what we pay for--more bytes meaning more security (unless they're from the NSA and trying to punk us).</p>
<h2>We Also Have Three <em>Insecure</em> Hashes...</h2>
<p>These are fine when you're doing something that is not supposed to be protecting against adversarial attacks.  They're smaller to store and much cheaper to calculate...but it's trivial to find other input data that would produces the same 32-bit result:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; checksum/method {DICKENS} 'crc32
== #{FB05F0BC}  ; used to very gzip files (among other places)

&gt;&gt; checksum/method {DICKENS} 'adler32
== #{0202D207}  ; used by zlib deflate and inflate
</code></pre>
<p>If you want a <em>really</em> cheapskate insecure checksum, we include the one that is in TCP packets on the internet:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; checksum/method {DICKENS} 'tcp
== #{CA32}
</code></pre>
<hr>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Fun Corner</strong>: Let's find a collision!</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; until [
    string: copy {}
    repeat (random 10) [append string make char! 64 + random 26]
    #{CA32} = checksum/method string 'tcp
]
== #[true]

&gt;&gt; print string
AOGTDDN

&gt;&gt; checksum/method {AOGTDDN} 'tcp
== #{CA32}
</code></pre>
<p>That wasn't so hard, but... if you can find collisions for any of the <em>secure</em> hashes above (even the relatively-weak MD5 or SHA1) <em>you will be famous!</em></p>
</blockquote>
<h2>We're Primed To Make <strong>STREAMING</strong> Secure (or Insecure) Hashes !</h2>
<p>R3-Alpha did not have fancy modern hashes like SHA256 or SHA512.  But also the code it used was copy-pasted out of a library that required you to have all the data at once.</p>
<p>Hence if you have a multi-gigabyte DVD .iso file that you want to checksum, you have to read that into a multi-gigabyte BINARY! to process it.</p>
<p>But since Ren-C is leveraging the cryptography of the <a href="https://github.com/Mbed-TLS/mbedtls">pure C library known as mbedTLS</a>, the foundations are there to stream in little blobs at a time...and it is generalized so we can just flip on or off any hashes we care about.  <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/what-is-a-port/617/5">If we only knew how to express streaming with PORT!s (or whatever)</a>.</p>
<p>And also, the CRC32 and ADLER32 algorithms we have "for free" by including Zlib are now set up in a way that the insecure hashes can be streamed too.</p>
<h2>
<img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/globe_with_meridians.png?v=9" title=":globe_with_meridians:" class="emoji" alt=":globe_with_meridians:"> <em>"How Does This Tie Into The Web Repl Story"?</em> <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/globe_with_meridians.png?v=9" title=":globe_with_meridians:" class="emoji" alt=":globe_with_meridians:">
</h2>
<p>I really want to have a laser focus on whether investing effort into something is going to be something that pays off or not, and to me a part of that payoff question is "will people using the web build care".</p>
<p><strong>Right now the web build does not include the CHECKSUM function at all.</strong>  <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/frowning.png?v=9" title=":frowning:" class="emoji" alt=":frowning:"></p>
<p>That is too bad, because I do believe that putting secure hashes into the hands of users at the Web Repl prompt (as well as other basic crypto parts) would be a great playground.</p>
<p>But it would be rather heavyweight to push secure hashing into the default .wasm being pulled down on every site if it didn't use it.  This is why I really want to get "Wasm extensions" working, that can be dynamically loaded.  There's something called "side modules" that I have meant to explore but haven't.</p>
<p>Anyway, I hope this summary gives a little insight into where this is at, and perhaps educational for those who don't have experience with the difference between secure/insecure hashing.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/checksums-and-secure-hashes-in-ren-c/1808">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/checksums-and-secure-hashes-in-ren-c/1808</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 04:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1808</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/checksums-and-secure-hashes-in-ren-c/1808.rss">Checksums and Secure Hashes in Ren-C</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Dropping RC4 Support from the Crypto Extension</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Cryptography</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I pretty sure no one out there is using it, but the RC4 cipher has been deprecated for a pretty long time now.  Per Wikipedia:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cryptography">cryptography</a>, <strong>RC4</strong> (Rivest Cipher 4 also known as <strong>ARC4</strong> or <strong>ARCFOUR</strong> meaning Alleged RC4, see below) is a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stream_cipher">stream cipher</a>. While it is remarkable for its simplicity and speed in software, multiple vulnerabilities have been discovered in RC4, rendering it insecure.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The insecurity of RC4 led the IETF to <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7465">prohibit RC4 for TLS use in 2015</a></p>
<p>However, the original cryptography code (mostly from AxTLS) had an RC4 function, and it was in mbedTLS 2.  So I went ahead and kept it working.</p>
<p>It is now dropped from mbedTLS 3.  So in the scheme of things, time to let it go.</p>
<h2>Code Being Dropped</h2>
<p>The files arc4.h and arc4.c from mbedTLS are now gone, and this was the crypt module code for supporting it:</p>
<pre><code>static void cleanup_rc4_ctx(const REBVAL *v)
{
    struct mbedtls_arc4_context *ctx
        = VAL_HANDLE_POINTER(struct mbedtls_arc4_context, v);
    mbedtls_arc4_free(ctx);
    FREE(struct mbedtls_arc4_context, ctx);
}


//
//  export rc4-key: native [
//
//  "Encrypt/decrypt data (modifies) using RC4 algorithm."
//
//      return: [handle!]
//      key [binary!]
//  ]
//
REBNATIVE(rc4_key)
//
// !!! RC4 was originally included for use with TLS.  However, the insecurity
// of RC4 led the IETF to prohibit RC4 for TLS use in 2015:
//
// https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7465
//
// So it is not in use at the moment.  It isn't much code, but could probably
// be moved to its own extension so it could be selected to build in or not,
// which is how cryptography methods should probably be done.
{
    CRYPT_INCLUDE_PARAMS_OF_RC4_KEY;

    struct mbedtls_arc4_context *ctx = TRY_ALLOC(struct mbedtls_arc4_context);
    mbedtls_arc4_init(ctx);

    REBSIZ key_len;
    const REBYTE *key = VAL_BINARY_SIZE_AT(&amp;key_len, ARG(key));
    mbedtls_arc4_setup(ctx, key, key_len);

    return Init_Handle_Cdata_Managed(
        D_OUT,
        ctx,
        sizeof(struct mbedtls_arc4_context),
        &amp;cleanup_rc4_ctx
    );
}


//
//  export rc4-stream: native [
//
//  "Encrypt/decrypt data (modifies) using RC4 algorithm."
//
//      return: &lt;none&gt;
//      ctx "Stream cipher context"
//          [handle!]
//      data "Data to encrypt/decrypt (modified)"
//          [binary!]
//  ]
//
REBNATIVE(rc4_stream)
{
    CRYPT_INCLUDE_PARAMS_OF_RC4_STREAM;

    REBVAL *data = ARG(data);

    if (VAL_HANDLE_CLEANER(ARG(ctx)) != cleanup_rc4_ctx)
        rebJumps ("fail [{Not a RC4 Context:}", ARG(ctx), "]");

    struct mbedtls_arc4_context *ctx
        = VAL_HANDLE_POINTER(struct mbedtls_arc4_context, ARG(ctx));

    REBVAL *error = nullptr;

    REBSIZ length;
    REBYTE *output = VAL_BINARY_SIZE_AT_ENSURE_MUTABLE(&amp;length, data);
    const REBYTE *input = output;
    IF_NOT_0(cleanup, error, mbedtls_arc4_crypt(
        ctx,
        length,
        input,  // input "message"
        output  // output (same, since it modifies)
    ));

  cleanup:
     if (error)
        rebJumps ("fail", error);

    return rebNone();
}
</code></pre>
<p>...and here is the very basic test, also being removed...</p>
<pre><code>ctx: rc4-key as binary! "Deprecated Algorithm"
data: as binary! "But Implemented Anyway"
rc4-stream ctx data
data = #{0C4E2F3BD157EA7214C33F280BE4D9DF1DFB580563A6}</code></pre>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/dropping-rc4-support-from-the-crypto-extension/1807">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/dropping-rc4-support-from-the-crypto-extension/1807</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 01:32:56 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1807</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/dropping-rc4-support-from-the-crypto-extension/1807.rss">Dropping RC4 Support from the Crypto Extension</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>About the Cryptography category</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Cryptography</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Discussion of things related to cryptography, which includes low level primitives (ciphers, hashes, and key exchange) as well as higher-level protocols such as TLS.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/about-the-cryptography-category/1806">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/about-the-cryptography-category/1806</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 01:11:25 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>Yes</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1806</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/about-the-cryptography-category/1806.rss">About the Cryptography category</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>REPL Querying</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Console</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>It might be worthwhile to take some inspiration from this:</p>
<aside class="onebox githubfolder">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://github.githubassets.com/favicons/favicon.svg" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">
      <a href="https://github.com/ellie/atuin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/345;"><img src="https://opengraph.githubassets.com/dca1958aebeb424b5526f3fa3c903c51716ab4f22eb7cd64a50259c3d4288398/ellie/atuin" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="345"></div>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/ellie/atuin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub - ellie/atuin:  Magical shell history</a></h3>


  <p><span class="label1"> Magical shell history. Contribute to ellie/atuin development by creating an account on GitHub.</span></p>

  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>I'd like us to start using the <a href="https://github.com/hostilefork/replpad-js/blob/master/storage.md">persistence features</a> to remember previous sessions, and perhaps make it easier to <strong>curate past Repl interactions into scripts</strong>.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/repl-querying/1804">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/repl-querying/1804</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 19:11:19 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1804</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/repl-querying/1804.rss">REPL Querying</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>LOGIN Magazine Historical Covers</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Offtopic</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Those who are interested in Rebol history might be interested in these magazine covers.  I am trying to delete files off a computer and had them, and if they have any relevance they are better backed up as part of the forum backups:</p>
<p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/original/1X/5385218e7af6c5e52f7dee3c114207f08668bbe4.jpeg" data-download-href="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/5385218e7af6c5e52f7dee3c114207f08668bbe4" title="rebol-login-nov-2001"><img src="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/5385218e7af6c5e52f7dee3c114207f08668bbe4_2_353x500.jpeg" alt="rebol-login-nov-2001" data-base62-sha1="bUQRrNKBWgwSAqtWhtOVp1zs0ks" width="353" height="500" srcset="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/5385218e7af6c5e52f7dee3c114207f08668bbe4_2_353x500.jpeg, https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/5385218e7af6c5e52f7dee3c114207f08668bbe4_2_529x750.jpeg 1.5x, https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/5385218e7af6c5e52f7dee3c114207f08668bbe4_2_706x1000.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/5385218e7af6c5e52f7dee3c114207f08668bbe4_2_10x10.png"><div class="meta">
<svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-far-image svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#far-image"></use></svg><span class="filename">rebol-login-nov-2001</span><span class="informations">14482048 534 KB</span><svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-discourse-expand svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#discourse-expand"></use></svg>
</div></a></div></p>
<p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/original/1X/19d65a0ef0878828180a88f3257fae3cc465db94.jpeg" data-download-href="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/19d65a0ef0878828180a88f3257fae3cc465db94" title="rebol-login-sep-2002"><img src="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/19d65a0ef0878828180a88f3257fae3cc465db94_2_353x500.jpeg" alt="rebol-login-sep-2002" data-base62-sha1="3GzbmOscS1RVPpGqNNJcrWd2PY0" width="353" height="500" srcset="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/19d65a0ef0878828180a88f3257fae3cc465db94_2_353x500.jpeg, https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/19d65a0ef0878828180a88f3257fae3cc465db94_2_529x750.jpeg 1.5x, https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/19d65a0ef0878828180a88f3257fae3cc465db94_2_706x1000.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://forum.rebol.info/uploads/default/optimized/1X/19d65a0ef0878828180a88f3257fae3cc465db94_2_10x10.png"><div class="meta">
<svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-far-image svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#far-image"></use></svg><span class="filename">rebol-login-sep-2002</span><span class="informations">14482048 488 KB</span><svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-discourse-expand svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#discourse-expand"></use></svg>
</div></a></div></p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/login-magazine-historical-covers/1803">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/login-magazine-historical-covers/1803</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 19:45:02 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1803</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/login-magazine-historical-covers/1803.rss">LOGIN Magazine Historical Covers</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>DO vs. IMPORT and &quot;Console-Extending Applications&quot;</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Modules</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>During the module reworking, I roughly embraced the R3-Alpha distinction made in the header between two categories:</p>
<hr>
<pre><code>Rebol [Type: Script ...]  ; first category
</code></pre>
<ul>
<li>
<p>You would run these "Scripts" with DO</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Performing a DO could have side effects, but should be isolated...not allowed to leak changes into the caller's environment</p>
<ul>
<li>This was a new rule I imposed as a default (because "Isolate" was made more economical, and I wanted to see how much we could get away with)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<pre><code>Rebol [Type: Module ...]  ; second category
</code></pre>
<ul>
<li>
<p>An "ideal" module would not have any "side-effects"...because the concept was that no matter how many times you run IMPORT you will only get one copy of that module in memory.</p>
<ul>
<li>Notably, if you run an IMPORT on a module that has already been loaded before...that will not run any code in the module body...it will just give you the MODULE! object that it already made.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>We probably shouldn't be surprised that there are things that don't fit neatly into these categories!</strong></p>
<hr>
<h2>"Console-Extending Applications"</h2>
<p>So these add some functions to your environment, but also tend to have some side effects.  Like:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong><a class="mention" href="/u/gchiu">@gchiu</a>'s chess program</strong> - It wants to display a board, show you some help, and add various chess-related behaviors to the console.  But to add those commands which "contaminate" the calling environment, you have to say <strong>import</strong>.  On the other hand, by displaying a board and showing help, it sort of violates that "no side-effects" rule.</p>
<ul>
<li>He is working on another prescription-generating application that lets you automate a pop-up window that works in a similar way.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>The ReplPad interactivity test</strong> - This test adds OKAY and NOPE to the vocabulary... where it's actually the typing of those words that runs commands which advance the console through steps in some way and instructs you on what to look for.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>If you don't use IMPORT, you don't get the commands added as commands to the context...</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>...but if you DO use IMPORT, you can only run through the test once... because doing it again will not load the code that prints out the instructions and launches it...</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2>Should DO allow you to EXPORT ?</h2>
<p>The nice thing about the word DO is it sounds pretty unambiguous, that you want to run something that has side effects.</p>
<p>But I do like the default of not leaking into the enclosing environment.</p>
<p>It seems like allowing scripts to export symbols could be a lazy compromise...which would let you ask to run something (vs. just bringing in a cached copy if previously loaded).</p>
<p>Yet this raises the question of what sort of behavior you'd expect from something that extends the console if you DO it multiple times.</p>
<p>There's also some things to think about regarding how modules will only load once, with respect to debugging.  If you have a complex multi-module project running and want to tweak something--reload it and retry without losing your current interpreter state, that's rather complicated semantically.</p>
<p>We might also consider the idea that there's a new script type.  Something like <strong><code>Rebol [Type: Commands ...]</code></strong> for lack of a better name.  Maybe this would by default give you a new console session separate from the one you were in?</p>
<p>Much more work is needed on binding and modules, to try and figure out how to deliver a good experience.  So hopefully if I don't die in a tornado here in Tennessee, I will work on that soon.  <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=9" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:"></p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/do-vs-import-and-console-extending-applications/1802">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/do-vs-import-and-console-extending-applications/1802</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 19:42:39 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1802</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/do-vs-import-and-console-extending-applications/1802.rss">DO vs. IMPORT and &quot;Console-Extending Applications&quot;</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Suppressing verbosity in the replpad</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[gchiu]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Emscripten</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I am developing a replpad app but I want the users to go straight to a URL and start the app.  I'd rather that they didn't have to type</p>
<pre><code>import @rx
</code></pre>
<p>when a lot of module stuff is sent to the console interrupting the interface, eg</p>
<pre><code>`== make module! [
    alpha: make bitset! #{00000000000000007FFFFFE07FFFFFE0}  
    rx: '#[action! {rx} [drug]]  
    ...  
</code></pre>
<p>`</p>
<p>Maybe <code>http://hostilefork.com/media/shared/replpad-js/@rx</code> would be better and if a module is provided then verbose mode is automatically suppressed.</p>
<p>Anyway, suggestions for a standardised way to run our apps?</p>
            <p><small>3 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/suppressing-verbosity-in-the-replpad/1801">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/suppressing-verbosity-in-the-replpad/1801</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 09:49:47 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1801</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/suppressing-verbosity-in-the-replpad/1801.rss">Suppressing verbosity in the replpad</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Conflation vs. Safety, RETURN and the Finer Points of ~null~ Isotopes</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Internals</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p><code>~null~</code> isotopes are a novel solution shaped to solve a specific problem.  As a reminder of what the goal is...</p>
<h1>The Goal is to Please <a class="mention" href="/u/rgchris">@rgchris</a> <em>AND</em> Please me</h1>
<p>NULL is the signal of "soft failure".  It's a unique result reserved for when a branch fails, or when a loop is halted by a BREAK, when PARSE fails...etc.</p>
<p>Its property of not being storable in blocks makes it critical to disambiguating this historical problem:</p>
<pre><code>redbol&gt;&gt; third [a b #[none]]
== #[none]

redbol&gt;&gt; third [a b]
== #[none]
</code></pre>
<p>In a language that prides itself on letting you work with code structure, <em>this is the tip of the iceberg of the problems that null solves</em>, and you will find the distinction's utility across the board (obviously, in tools like COMPOSE).  It facilitates rigorous analysis and rearrangements...without needing to drop to C or write convoluted code:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; third [a b _]
== _

&gt;&gt; third [a b]
; null
</code></pre>
<p>Hence NULL has taken the place of blank ("none!") in many places, one of which is the unique result of failed conditionals.</p>
<p>But unlike the elements in a block, a branch that evaluates isn't required to be non-NULL.  Which leads us to the long running question of what to bend NULL branches to so they don't conflate with the branch-not-taken result.</p>
<h2>Chris has (rightly) expressed concern</h2>
<p>At times I've said that it's not that big a deal that branches can't evaluate to NULL and get distorted.  "You didn't have a NULL before, so why get so worked up about control constructs not returning it?"</p>
<p>But the now-pervasive nature of NULL means it can't be avoided.  So:</p>
<p><em>"How do you express branching code which wants to do some work but also produce NULL as an evaluative product?"</em></p>
<p>Conflation was not a problem, e.g. in Rebol2:</p>
<pre><code>rebol2&gt;&gt; exampler: func [x] [
     print "returning sample or none if not found"
     case [
         x = &lt;string&gt; [print "sample string" {hello}]
         x = &lt;integer&gt; [print "sample integer" 3]
         x = &lt;none&gt; [print "sample none" none]
     ]
  ]

rebol2&gt;&gt; exampler &lt;string&gt;
returning sample or none if not found
sample string
== "hello"

rebol2&gt;&gt; exampler &lt;blatz&gt;
returning sample or none if not found
== #[none]

rebol2&gt;&gt; exampler &lt;none&gt;
returning sample or none if not found
sample none
== #[none]
</code></pre>
<p>However NULL is now the basic currency of "soft failure".  As such it would not be uncommon to be in the situation where a branching decision process would want to intentionally return NULL as part of the work it does.</p>
<p>Without something like the isotope decay mechanism, unpleasant convolutions would be needed, for instance surrounding anything that wanted to tunnel a NULL with a CATCH and THROW'ing it:</p>
<pre><code>x: catch [
    throw switch 1 + 2 [
        1 [print "one" 1]
        2 [print "two", &lt;two&gt;]
        3 [print "three", throw null]
     ]
]
</code></pre>
<p>Definitely not good.  But regarding the pleasing-me-part, remember I am trying to avoid this situation:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; case [
     true [
          print "case branch"
          if 1 &gt; 2 [print "failed inner"]
     ]
   ] else [
     print "else branch"
   ]

case branch
else branch  ; ugh
</code></pre>
<p>I don't want the CASE branch to evaluate to NULL just because the failed IF inside the branch was NULL.  That would mean the ELSE tied to the CASE runs even though the code for the branch ran.</p>
<h2>Enter Isotopes</h2>
<p>One thing null isotopes have in common with NULL (like all BAD-WORD! isotopes) is that they can't be put in blocks.  But they have been automatically "decaying" into regular NULL when stored into variables.</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; ~null~
== ~null~  ; isotope

&gt;&gt; x: ~null~
== ~null~  ; isotope  &lt;-- note the overall expression is still an isotope

&gt;&gt; x
; null
</code></pre>
<p>The twist is that they are <em>different enough</em> from true NULL such that a THEN or an ELSE can consider them a situation where the branch did not run:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; if false [&lt;ignored&gt;]
; null

&gt;&gt; if true [null]
== ~null~  ; isotope

&gt;&gt; if true [null] else [print "This won't run"]
== ~null~  ; isotope
</code></pre>
<p>The reason functions like ELSE can "see" the isotope is that they don't take an ordinary parameter on their left.  They take a ^META argument.  These can see the distinction between a ~null~ isotope and a "true" NULL.</p>
<p><strong>I'd largely say this has been working well...certainly better than its conceptual predecessors.</strong>  It makes piping NULL out of branches trivially easy, when the fear of conflation is not a problem.</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; x: switch 1 + 2 [
     1 [print "one" 1]
     2 [print "two", &lt;two&gt;]
     3 [print "three", null]
   ]
three
== ~null~

&gt;&gt; x
; null
</code></pre>
<p>The automatic decay in variable storage prevents you from needing an explicit operation to turn ~null~ isotopes into pure nulls:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; x: decay switch 1 + 2 [
     1 [print "one" 1]
     2 [print "two", &lt;two&gt;]
     3 [print "three", null]
   ]
three
; null
</code></pre>
<h1>But <a class="mention" href="/u/rgchris">@rgchris</a> Would Likely Want any <em>NORMAL</em> arg decay</h1>
<p>At the very moment I am writing this, ~null~ isotopes are like all other BAD-WORD! isotopes and not accepted as normal parameters.</p>
<p><strong>They <em>could</em> decay to pure NULL for all normal args.</strong>  But let me explain a bummer of what we lose in that bargain.</p>
<p>It takes away a safety idea I had with functions like MATCH.</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; match [&lt;opt&gt; integer!] 3
== 3

&gt;&gt; match [&lt;opt&gt; integer!] "notaninteger"
; null

&gt;&gt; match [&lt;opt&gt; integer!] null
== ~null~  ; isotope
</code></pre>
<p>The idea was that it could say "yes, this matched" but if ~null~ isotopes were tested, they'd give an error:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; if (match [&lt;opt&gt; integer!] null) [print "Yes it matched!"]
** Error: IF does not accept ~null~ isotopes without a ^META condition
</code></pre>
<p>Were MATCH to have passed through a plain NULL it would have succeeded in the match but not run the branch.  So it's nice to get the warning on the isotope.</p>
<p><strong>Or it could just return a ~matched~ isotope</strong>.  But this loses the following nice isotopic property:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; x: match [&lt;opt&gt; integer!] null else [fail "NO MATCH"]
== ~null~  ; isotope

&gt;&gt; x
; null
</code></pre>
<p>In fact I instituted other decaying variants for ~blank~ and ~false~</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; y: match [blank!] _ else [fail "NO MATCH!"]
== ~blank~  ; isotope

&gt;&gt; y
== _

&gt;&gt; z: match [logic!] 1 = 2 else [fail "NO MATCH!"]
== ~false~  ; isotope

&gt;&gt; z
== #[false]
</code></pre>
<h1>So What To Do About MATCH and its bretheren?</h1>
<p>Seems the options are:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><em>Don't worry about it.</em>  If you write <strong>match [logic!] 1 = 2</strong> you get back <strong>#[false]</strong> and should you write an expression like <strong>if (match [logic!] 1 = 2) [print "Match!]</strong> you get what you deserve.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Use a different isotope.</em>  Let's say that <strong><code>match [&lt;opt&gt;] null</code></strong> is simply <strong>~matched~ (isotope)</strong>.  It wouldn't have the decaying property, but would have the invalidness property.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Have a MATCH/FALSEY variant.</em>  Let plain <strong>match</strong> on a falsey thing trigger an error and if you write <strong>if match/falsey ...</strong> then you clearly do know what you're doing so it becomes like case (1).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em>Make all conditional arguments take ^META arguments for their conditions.</em>  This would put the responsibility for checking for isotopes on them, and they'd uniquely disallow them before UNMETA'ing them and then testing for truth/falsehood.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Option (4) is too taxing...impacting not just the interface to IF but the implementation of CASE and any conditional construct.</p>
<p><strong>I think I like (3) because it punts the ball down the road a bit.</strong></p>
<p>But this might still not suit Chris.</p>
<h1>Should Non-Meta Arguments Decay Null isotopes?</h1>
<p>The "auto-decay" of ~null~ isotopes means no variable can ever hold a NULL isotope.  And there's also a rule that no <em>normal</em> parameter can ever be passed an isotope, only ^META parameters.</p>
<p>In the beginning, it seemed useful if normal arguments would automatically decay null isotopes:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; foo: func [x] [if null? x [print "Yup, it's null"]]

&gt;&gt; foo if true [null]
Yup it's null

&gt;&gt; metafoo: func [^x] [
    case [
        null? x [print "regular null"]
        x = '~null~ [print "null isotope"]
        true [print "something else"]
     ]
   ]

&gt;&gt; metafoo if false [null]
regular null

&gt;&gt; metafoo if true [null]
null isotope
</code></pre>
<p>There is a manual DECAY operator which could be used, but would not meet that wish:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; ~null~
== ~null~  ; isotope

&gt;&gt; decay ~null~
; null

&gt;&gt; ~blank~
== ~blank~  ; isotope

&gt;&gt; decay ~blank~
== _

&gt;&gt; ~false~
== ~false~  ; isotope

&gt;&gt; decay ~false~
== #[false]
</code></pre>
<h1>Should DECAY Conflation Be A Customization?</h1>
<p>Another avenue of satisfaction could be to say that you simply customize your environment with some definitions to make auto-decaying constructs:</p>
<pre><code>switch: chain [:switch | :decay]
case: chain [:case | :decay]
...

&gt;&gt; case [true [null]]
; null

&gt;&gt; case [false [10]]
; null
</code></pre>
<p>I don't like it, but if someone isn't going to use ELSE (or is willing to accept this very easily unintentional conflation if they do) it could be an option.</p>
<p><strong>I really do believe the ability to tell from outside the construct if a branch has been taken is an interesting property, which even those who think they won't use ELSE or THEN can leverage, especially when building constructs atop each other.</strong>  But this isn't something that can be appreciated without usage, or trying to write something like UPARSE generically in usermode.</p>
<h1>Should function RETURN decay by default?</h1>
<p>Continuing along these lines, this has to do with the pattern of:</p>
<pre><code>foo: func [x] [
    return switch x [
         1 [print "one", #one]
         2 [print "two", null]
         3 [print "three", &lt;three&gt;]
    ]
]

&gt;&gt; foo 1 + 2
two
== ???   ; should this be ~null~ isotope or just NULL
</code></pre>
<p>Also, should it matter whether there's a RETURN there or not?  Is this something the type spec should distinguish?</p>
<p>Right now there's a refinement called /ISOTOPE on RETURN which asks it not to decay.</p>
<p><strong>If all non-^META parameters decay by default, then it seems isotopic decay is the right default for RETURN even though it takes a ^META parameter and returns non-decaying isotopes.</strong></p>
<h2>As Always, A Lot To Think About</h2>
<p>Want to get this posted because it's preventing me from making new drafts (Discourse won't let you have multiple top-level post drafts in-flight for some reason).</p>
<p>Will keep mulling it all over.</p>
<p><em>"A designer knows he has achieved perfection not when there is nothing left to add, but when there is nothing left to take away."</em></p>
            <p><small>3 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/conflation-vs-safety-return-and-the-finer-points-of-null-isotopes/1799">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/conflation-vs-safety-return-and-the-finer-points-of-null-isotopes/1799</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2022 04:14:06 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1799</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/conflation-vs-safety-return-and-the-finer-points-of-null-isotopes/1799.rss">Conflation vs. Safety, RETURN and the Finer Points of ~null~ Isotopes</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Rebmu History Removed from File (is History: a good idea?)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Rebmu</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>When I started Rebmu I followed along the pattern of having seen people put <strong><code>History:</code></strong> in the headers of files.  And as it got longer, I kind of questioned the value of it.</p>
<p>I'm not sure what the "best practices" for history is, but it's a lot of stuff to skip over when you're trying to get to the meat of a file.  It warrants its own discussion topic (which I guess can be discussed here, with the extracted history).</p>
<pre><code>History: [
    0.1.0 [10-Jan-2010 {Sketchy prototype written to cover only the
    Roman Numeral example I worked through when coming up with the
    idea.  So very incomplete, more a proof of concept.}]

    0.2.0 [22-Jun-2010 {Language more complete, includes examples.
    Ditched concept of mushing symbols like + and - into single
    character operators is removed due to realization that A+
    B+ C+ etc. are more valuable in the symbol space than one
    character for AD.}]

    0.3.0 [24-Jun-2010 {Made backwards compatible with Rebol 2.
    Note that things like CN for continue or PERCENTAGE! datatype
    were added in Rebol 3.  You can use these in your Rebmu programs
    but they will only work if using Rebmu with an r3 interpreter.
    Also did several name tweaks like instead of AA for AND~ it's
    now A~ along with other consistencies.}]

    0.5.0 [16-Feb-2014 {Version bump to indicate growing maturity
    of the language.  Abandon Rebol 2 support.  Rebmu files now
    have proper Rebol ecology headers.}]

    0.6.0 [6-Apr-2014 {Large cleanup creating incompatibility with
    most all previous Rebmu code solutions.  Examples have been updated
    in GitHub.  Major theme was removing the custom IF/UNLESS/EITHER
    implementation and some clearer names.}]

    0.7.0 [15-Sep-2015 {Project revisited to incorporate new ideas and
    decisions from the Ren/C effort.  Incorporates the rebol-proposals
    module to work with experimental language features instead of
    having its own "incubator" project.  "Mu library" features removed
    in favor of embracing the language default more closely.}]
]</code></pre>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebmu-history-removed-from-file-is-history-a-good-idea/1798">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebmu-history-removed-from-file-is-history-a-good-idea/1798</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 08:22:26 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1798</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebmu-history-removed-from-file-is-history-a-good-idea/1798.rss">Rebmu History Removed from File (is History: a good idea?)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Symbols and Mushing in Rebmu</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Rebmu</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>There are symbols like &amp; and | which were applied somewhat haphazardly in the original Rebmu, as experiments.</p>
<p>For instance, <strong>&amp;</strong> was a shortcut for DOES.</p>
<pre><code>phi: does [print "hi"]
=&gt;
PHI &amp;[print "hi"]
</code></pre>
<p>(There've been murmurs of other uses for &amp;, but no hard decisions on it yet...and even if it were used for HTML characters like <strong>&amp;nbsp</strong>, it might remain free standalone as a symbol.)</p>
<p>For a time, <strong>|</strong> in Ren-C was not something you could redefine as a WORD!, it was its own datatype "BAR!".  But that has been replaced by the successful COMMA!, retaking it as a word.  It was used in function definition, and some of the contractions I've suggested as things like <strong><code>fqC[...]</code></strong> =&gt; <strong>function [a b c] [...]</strong> were contracted as simply <strong><code>c|[...]</code></strong></p>
<p>There was a handling of dots which allowed a quick way of doing redefinitions:</p>
<pre><code>     .[aBCdEF] =&gt; .[a bc d ef] =&gt; a: :bc d: :ef
</code></pre>
<p>There's still some back-and-forth on the handling of lone dot.  I like it being a reduced case of a TUPLE! in some sense...because it makes it easier to write generic fusing code for things like JOIN.  But putting into the new SYMBOL! class (which cannot appear in TUPLE! or PATH!) might have advantages, and helpers to count the dots might serve just as well.</p>
<p>I'm not sure what the in-language default function for plain dot will be, but it's likely that it will not be more powerful than either <strong>.a</strong> or <strong>a.</strong> enough to justify that <strong>a.a</strong> should be interpreted as <strong>a . a</strong>.</p>
<p>It's important to look at the specifics of mushing with symbols as they have no case, so the breakapart rules are different.  I've diagrammed some of these before.</p>
<pre><code>a+b =&gt; a+b  ; compatibility with all lowercase code
a+B =&gt; a+ b  ; favors breaking to the left, vs. a +b
</code></pre>
<p>I'll delve into these justifications, but since I'm deleting the old definitions of things like <strong>a&amp;</strong> and <strong>a|</strong> I wanted to put a placeholder topic for discussing it.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/symbols-and-mushing-in-rebmu/1797">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/symbols-and-mushing-in-rebmu/1797</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 08:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1797</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/symbols-and-mushing-in-rebmu/1797.rss">Symbols and Mushing in Rebmu</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Rebmu&#39;s FUNQTION (FQ): Dialecting Function Definition Itself</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Rebmu</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <blockquote>
<p>After writing this I realized I had <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/function-mu-rebmus-function-generator-dialect/1379">already written a post about this in 2020</a>, but... here it is again, I guess!  Maybe I said it better or worse this time?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>(Note: FQ is pronounced EFF-QUEUE, say it carefully. <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=9" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:">)</em></p>
<p>So in Rebmu, <strong>FN</strong> is a superset of <strong>FUNC</strong> (itself a synonym for <strong>FUNCTION</strong>).</p>
<p>It doesn't do anything <em>terribly</em> tricky because its arguments are both evaluative.  So you can pass it specs and bodies that are variables.  Here's a useless example of taking advantage of that with a spec in a variable:</p>
<pre><code>; define a spec which takes two arguments
S[xY]   ; =&gt; s: [x y]

; define function A that adds X and Y.
AfnS[adXy]  ; =&gt; a: fn s [ad x y]
            ; =&gt; a: function s [add x y]

; define function M that multiplies X and Y
MfnS[mpXy]  ; =&gt; m: fn s [mp x y]
            ; =&gt; m: function s [multiply x y]
</code></pre>
<p><em>...but what might a Code-Golf-Dialected FUNQTION (FQ) Do, unbound by rote evaluation of its parameters?</em>  Let's use our imagination...</p>
<h2>A Quoted Spec could permit Spec Compression</h2>
<p>How about if you gave a WORD! that was a letter and a number, you'd get 3 args starting with that letter?</p>
<pre><code>fqR3[adMPrSt]
; =&gt; fq r3 [ad mp r s t]
; =&gt; fn [r s t] [ad mp r s t]
; =&gt; function [r s t] [add multiply r s t]
; =&gt; function [r s t] [add (multiply r s) t]
</code></pre>
<p>That's a three character savings vs. having to express the block for <strong>[r s t]</strong> explicitly with a plain function:</p>
<pre><code>fn[rSt][adMPrSt]
</code></pre>
<p>If you didn't include a number that might be a different memoization of what the arguments were, such as:</p>
<pre><code>fqA[...] =&gt; fn [a] [...]
fqB[...] =&gt; fn [a b] [...]
fqC[...] =&gt; fn [a b c] [...]

fqX[...] =&gt; fn [z y x] [...]
fqY[...] =&gt; fn [z y] [...]
fqZ[...] =&gt; fn [z] [...]
</code></pre>
<p>The idea being that you need to sort of spread out your variable names in code golf, for instance when working with nested functions.  From a tactical standpoint one might be served to throw in curveballs:</p>
<pre><code>fqM[...] =&gt; fn [m j z] [...]
</code></pre>
<p>Though that lessens the readability/learnability.  Anyway, what else...?</p>
<h2>Variadically Quoted Bodies Could Circumvent Brackets</h2>
<p>Let's say if it found a word in the slot where the body block would ordinarily be, it would treat that as a function that should be called.</p>
<p>To make it easier, let's just think about this un-Rebmu'd:</p>
<pre><code>foo: func [x y z] [any [x y z]]

bar: funq [x y z] any [x y z]
</code></pre>
<p>If FUNQ is variadic and quoting its body slot, it could notice the body does not contain a block but a WORD!.  Seeing that function is ANY, it could count the number of parameters ANY needs and pick them up from the callsite.</p>
<p><em>Such mechanics are within reach using today's FRAME!s</em>, in fact <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/looking-into-a-usermode-pointfree/1236">they are used by things like POINTFREE</a>...itself clearly useful in Rebmu.</p>
<h2>What Else Might FQ do?</h2>
<p>There's also things like GROUP!s, and <strong>fq(x)...</strong> could imply a completely different thing from <strong>fq[x]...</strong>, suggesting a mode switch in how the ensuing information is interpreted.</p>
<p>Or <strong>fqX(...)</strong> and <strong>fqX[...]</strong> could be completely different.  What about strings?  How might string interpolation fit into all of this?</p>
<pre><code>ZfqC{Implicit printing of $a and $b and $c?}
; =&gt; z: fn [a b c] [print interpolate {Implicit print of $a and $b and $c}]
</code></pre>
<p>Maybe the implicit printing is different, like FP, and FQ with a string simply interpolates it.</p>
<p><strong>Hopefully you get the drift.</strong>  I'm talking about making Rebmu a powerhouse showcase of what Ren-C is driving at.</p>
<p>How can quoting, variadics, frames, interpolation, and all of that be applied to dialecting the act of function definition itself?</p>
<h1><code>[insert your ideas here]</code></h1>
            <p><small>2 posts - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebmus-funqtion-fq-dialecting-function-definition-itself/1796">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebmus-funqtion-fq-dialecting-function-definition-itself/1796</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 07:07:04 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1796</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/rebmus-funqtion-fq-dialecting-function-definition-itself/1796.rss">Rebmu&#39;s FUNQTION (FQ): Dialecting Function Definition Itself</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>What was REBMU-WRAP (and why we no longer need it)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Rebmu</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>As I bring the Rebmu dialect up to date I'll try and talk about any teachable moments that it provides.</p>
<p>Let's look at one of the earliest weird functions, REBMU-WRAP:</p>
<pre><code>rebmu-wrap: function [refined [path!] args [block!]] [
    func args compose [
        (refined) (args)
    ]
]
</code></pre>
<p>It was designed to make it (slightly) easier to define something like <code>APO</code> as a synonym for <code>APPEND/ONLY</code>.</p>
<pre><code>APO: rebmu-wrap 'append/only [series value]
</code></pre>
<p>So that turns into effectively:</p>
<pre><code>APO: func [series value] [
    append/only series value
]
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Basically this was an incredibly weak way to save a few characters while making a partial specialization.</strong>  Some of its weaknesses:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>You still have to specify the number and names of arguments the specialization takes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If you make a mistake at the time of definition (like mentioning an unavailable refinement) you don't get the error until the call.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The other refinements are missing from the wrapped function, e.g. you can't invoke <code>apo/part</code> or <code>apo/dup</code>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You don't inherit anything about the original function's parameter conventions; e.g. if an argument were quoted you'd get the parameter name word you passed for it.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Performance-wise you generate a whole new function call...path evaluation...argument evaluation...</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Your new function doesn't have any HELP... etc. etc.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2>How To Make This Better in Classical "Redbol"?</h2>
<p>Let's put yourself in the mind of someone thinking about how I was at that time, <em>who wanted to use the same strategy but merely address (1) and (2)</em>.  So to be able to write the slightly shorter hand:</p>
<pre><code>APO: rebmu-wrap 'append/only
APD: rebmu-wrap 'append/dup
APDP: rebmu-wrap 'append/dup/part
APPD: rebmu-wrap 'append/part/dup  ; ...etc.
</code></pre>
<p>This version of REBMU-WRAP would need to analyze the spec, presumably with WORDS-OF:</p>
<pre><code>r3-alpha&gt;&gt; words-of :append
== [series value /part length /only /dup count]
</code></pre>
<p>So you might try something like the following nightmare...<strong>which took me at least an hour to write and debug!</strong> (probably more like two, because of the glitch of trying to mutate the spec in place and needing to notice when the insertion position matches the position a refinement argument is being moved from):</p>
<pre><code>rebmu-wrap: func [refined [path!] /local spec body pos insert-pos item] [
    if not any-function? (action: get first refined) [
        do make error! "first element of path must refer to a function"
    ]
    spec: words-of :action
    body: reduce [refined]
    insert-pos: spec  ; find where refinement args should be inserted
    while [all [not tail? insert-pos not refinement? insert-pos/1]][
        append body insert-pos/1
        insert-pos: next insert-pos
    ]
    foreach refinement-name (next refined) [
        if not pos: find spec to-refinement refinement-name [
            do make error! "missing or duplicate refinement specified"
        ]
        take pos  ; drop refinement from spec
        while [all [not tail? pos not refinement? pos/1 pos != insert-pos]] [
             insert-pos: insert insert-pos item: take pos
             append body item
        ]
    ]
    func ?? spec ?? body
]
</code></pre>
<p>If you try this in R3-Alpha, yes it does indeed work for (1) and (2). I put in the probes so you can see the spec and body of the new function:</p>
<pre><code>r3-alpha&gt;&gt; apo: rebmu-wrap 'append/only
spec: [series value /part length /dup count]
body: [append/only series value]

r3-alpha&gt; apd: rebmu-wrap 'append/dup
spec: [series value count /part length /only]
body: [append/dup series value count]

r3-alpha&gt;&gt; apdp: rebmu-wrap 'append/dup/part
spec: [series value count length /only]
body: [append/dup/part series value count]

r3-alpha&gt;&gt; appd: rebmu-wrap 'append/part/dup
spec: [series value count length /only]
body: [append/part/dup series value count]
</code></pre>
<p>It gets a head-start on (3) by leaving the refinements that haven't been partially specialized on the spec, but they're ignored in the call.</p>
<h2>That's A Lot Of Work for Something That Still Sucks! <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/nauseated_face.png?v=9" title=":nauseated_face:" class="emoji" alt=":nauseated_face:">
</h2>
<p>When you think of everything it entails to get (3) and (4), you are going to either need to COMPOSE your invocation on each call -or- change methodology to use APPLY.  But even if you are aware of APPLY it doesn't make this a trivial exercise, and doesn't help with (5) or (6).</p>
<p><strong>...and this is why I never even tried to write such things (before)... instead trying to add core interpreter features for partial specialization.</strong></p>
<h2>The Happy New World of Partial Specialization <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/sun_with_face.png?v=9" title=":sun_with_face:" class="emoji" alt=":sun_with_face:">
</h2>
<p>In today's Ren-C, all you have to do is get a function as a path, and you have (1) (2) (3) (4) (5).</p>
<pre><code>ren-c&gt;&gt; ap: :append
 == #[action! {ap} [series value /part /dup /line /only]]

ren-c&gt;&gt; ap [a b c] [d e]
== [a b c d e]

ren-c&gt;&gt; apo: :append/only
== #[action! {apo} [series value /part /dup /line]]

ren-c&gt;&gt; apo [a b c] [d e]
== [a b c [d e]]

ren-c&gt;&gt; apo/dup [a b c] [d e] 2  ; e.g. demonstrating (3)
== [a b c [d e] [d e]]
</code></pre>
<p>The new function call is just as efficient as the original (you might think of it moreso since there's no path processing, e.g. <strong>apo</strong> is faster than invoking <strong>ap/only</strong>!)</p>
<p>You don't get the HELP inherited automatically (it has an associated cost), but there is a function that will do it if you want to... you say <strong>inherit-meta :apo :append</strong> and then <strong>help apo</strong> will have the help strings copied into its meta information.</p>
<p>So that's some assistance with (6), but do remember that it's not a perfect world when talking about how to automatically write meaningful adjusted help.  If any parameter descriptions refer to the argument you specialized out, it's no longer on the interface, so they may not make sense!</p>
<p><em>(Note: Now that refinements are their own arguments, you can't tell by parameter list alone if a refinement is a 0 or 1 arg case.  It's determined by the typeset: if the typeset is empty--no types accepted--it is a 0 arg refinement.  Something to ponder if this can be done better, but see all the other nice things...like caching the label of the function name for stack traces, etc.)</em></p>
<h2>So long, REBMU-WRAP...</h2>
<p>...but I wanted to write this up just to show a good example of how early experiences playing with Rebmu led me to question Rebol, and want to shore up its abilities.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Beware of the Turing tar-pit in which <strong>everything is possible but nothing of interest is easy</strong>."</p>
</blockquote>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/what-was-rebmu-wrap-and-why-we-no-longer-need-it/1795">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/what-was-rebmu-wrap-and-why-we-no-longer-need-it/1795</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 06:06:27 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1795</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/what-was-rebmu-wrap-and-why-we-no-longer-need-it/1795.rss">What was REBMU-WRAP (and why we no longer need it)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>About the Rebmu category</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Rebmu</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Rebmu is a dialect for solving <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_golf">Code Golf challenges</a>, where the goal is to express the source code for solving a puzzle in the fewest characters of source code possible.  See the README here:</p>
<aside class="onebox githubfolder">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://github.githubassets.com/favicons/favicon.svg" class="site-icon" width="32" height="32">
      <a href="https://github.com/hostilefork/rebmu" target="_blank" rel="noopener">github.com</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/345;"><img src="https://opengraph.githubassets.com/1d67e812b647b23547cabb9d53af90f2917089ce3978ae8f525e7b31a26b475d/hostilefork/rebmu" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="345"></div>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/hostilefork/rebmu" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub - hostilefork/rebmu: Microscopic Rebol Dialect ("mooshed") for Code Golf</a></h3>


  <p><span class="label1">Microscopic Rebol Dialect ("mooshed") for Code Golf</span></p>

  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>Significant design points in Ren-C were inspired by wanting to make the implementation and bending of Rebmu more effective.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/about-the-rebmu-category/1794">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/about-the-rebmu-category/1794</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 04:15:56 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>Yes</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1794</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/about-the-rebmu-category/1794.rss">About the Rebmu category</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>(No) Alternative Local Notation in the Func Spec Dialect</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Dialects/DSLs</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <h1>TL;DR:</h1>
<p>When using a spec in FUNCTION (remember <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/abbreviations-as-synonyms/1211">FUNC is a synonym now</a>):</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>if you want to specify locals you say <code>[... &lt;local&gt; x y z ...]</code></strong> (/LOCAL is a normal refinement like any other in Ren-C.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>there is no longer a datatype-based shortcut for locals as a way to save the trouble of finding <code>&lt;local&gt;</code> in specs and inserting at the right point</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Once you could toss random SET-WORD!s anywhere in a spec, like <strong><code>[a b c: d]</code></strong> and it would act like <strong><code>[a b d &lt;local&gt; c]</code></strong>.  This feature was to make higher-level function generators easier to write, to save them from having to find <code>&lt;local&gt;</code> in the spec...add it if not there...and do everything at the right point.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When multi-returns began using SET-WORD! this was changed to be <strong><code>[a b .c d]</code></strong> just to move it out of the way.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>What this was trying to achieve has been obsoleted by newer and better methods, which actually entwine with the idea that <em>you should never know what local variables a function you are composing on top of has</em>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h1>More Explanation</h1>
<p>Long ago, when I was looking at some of the higher-level function generators (like FUNCT on top of FUNCTION) I was struck by how tricky it was to get the adaptations written correctly.</p>
<p>We can look at <a href="https://github.com/rebol/rebol/blob/25033f897b2bd466068d7663563cd3ff64740b94/src/mezz/base-funcs.r#L28">FUNCT from R3-Alpha</a> and see some of that complexity, even just to try and add some local variables.</p>
<p>It had to check to see if there was already a /LOCAL, and add it if not:</p>
<pre><code>; Copy the spec and add /local to the end if not found
unless find spec: copy/deep spec /local [append spec [
	/local ; In a block so the generated source gets the newlines
]]
</code></pre>
<p><em>Bear in mind that specifying /LOCAL twice would be a duplicate refinement error, and /LOCAL did not have to be at the end of a spec.</em>  Things were tricky, because there were "private refinements".  These refinements were an artifact of how help worked--they were not shown--but weren't actually private.</p>
<p>So you had to be careful, to insert things after local but not after the private refinements, or they'd be arguments to those refinements:</p>
<pre><code>; Collect all set-words in the body as words to be used as locals, and add
; them to the spec. Don't include the words already in the spec or object.
insert find/tail spec /local collect-words/deep/set/ignore body either with [
   ...
]
</code></pre>
<p><strong>I wanted to take better advantage of datatypes, so I adopted the TAG! <code>&lt;local&gt;</code> in the spec so that /LOCAL could be used like any other refinement... e.g. GET-TIME/LOCAL or GET-LANGUAGE/LOCAL.</strong>  This is an idea preserved to this day, and I think it's a better move (though LET has been developing as the more viable general option for making locals).</p>
<p>But another concept I had was to make SET-WORD! in the dialect be another way to put a local anywhere in the spec.  So if you were writing code munging function specs you could just throw local variables on:</p>
<pre><code>foo: func [a b c: d] [...]

&lt;= equivalent to =&gt;

foo: func [a b d &lt;local&gt; c] [...]
</code></pre>
<p>But the idea was that <code>&lt;local&gt;</code> itself was transformed into the SET-WORD!, so the only language you needed to understand was that of the SET-WORD!s:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; foo: func [a b d &lt;local&gt; c] [...]

&gt;&gt; spec-of :foo
== [a b d c:]
</code></pre>
<p>When multi-returns came about and took SET-WORD!s, this idea was bumped around to be done with TUPLE!s with leading blanks like <strong>.c</strong></p>
<h1><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2q9MaEKHakY">... but Everything Changed <img src="https://forum.rebol.info/images/emoji/twitter/robot.png?v=9" title=":robot:" class="emoji" alt=":robot:"> ...</a></h1>
<p>I've been marching toward something more like <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/seeing-all-action-s-as-variadic-frame-makers/1002">"Seeing all ACTION!s as Variadic Frame Makers?"</a></p>
<p>Function composition tools operate on FRAME!s using tools like ADAPT, SPECIALIZE, AUGMENT, ENCLOSE, etc.  There is no API for getting at the locals <em>because when you build on top of a function you can't see them, they're not part of the interface...they are sealed inside.</em>   This is good because you can build on top of a function without worrying about the details of the parts from which it was composed.</p>
<p>The migration to where <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/pure-and-refined-simplifying-refinements-to-one-or-zero-args/1120">refinements are their own arguments</a> has been key in making function calls easier to model as an object.</p>
<p><strong>In this world we do not need a representation for locals in the spec to add them...because the entire concept of how FUNCT was written is gone.</strong>  If you want to add locals you use tools like AUGMENT and don't worry about it.</p>
<h1>There Are Still (many) Problems To Solve</h1>
<p>Consider that you can do something like ask for a FRAME! of something like APPEND, then enumerate the keys:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; f: make frame! :append

&gt;&gt; for-each key f [print mold key]
return
series
value
part
dup
line
only
</code></pre>
<p>There are a lot of questions to answer about the unique nature of the main function's RETURN.  Although other multi-returns have to be on the interface, should you be able to put a variable in that return?  Consider that you could use multi-return with append today:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; [var]: append "abc" "d"
== "abcd"

&gt;&gt; var
== "abcd"
</code></pre>
<p>So should you be able to preload the frame with <strong>f.return: 'var</strong> and get the same effect?  This is competitive with the notion that RETURN is a concept of a local variable to the action, that holds an action that returns specifically from that action... so the responsibilities are somewhat murky for this distinguished result.</p>
<p>But we can also see that if we only look at object keys, we don't know which things are refinements or which are not...if they are refinements we don't know if they are 0-arg or 1-arg form, we don't know what types they take... or are they <code>&lt;end&gt;</code>-able.  <strong>I believe getting at this information should be done by means other than analysis of some spec block you filter out for description strings/etc. so that is on the right track.</strong>  But it's still a long road.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/no-alternative-local-notation-in-the-func-spec-dialect/1793">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/no-alternative-local-notation-in-the-func-spec-dialect/1793</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 20:33:12 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1793</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/no-alternative-local-notation-in-the-func-spec-dialect/1793.rss">(No) Alternative Local Notation in the Func Spec Dialect</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>My Summary of the Big Picture</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>First Steps</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I wrote this to someone in a GitHub issue and thought it was pretty salient:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What has drawn people to Rebol historically has varied. But a large number who praised it and used it were less interested in the language itself, rather the properties of the executable. It was small, and you could run on any OS without installing anything else...it came with a GUI built in.</p>
<p>But when serious language theorists look at Rebol, they notice it is riddled with design holes. The language itself wasn't <em>composable</em> the way one might like languages to be: mixing constructs in new ways that weren't specifically accounted for never worked. It was more like a "scriptable app" that had a few features that pleased its userbase...and had to be extended by the designer every time a new need came up.</p>
<p>So put briefly: If you don't understand what these holes are, then you won't appreciate the many issues that Ren-C is trying to solve. Starting from scratch inevitably makes the same mistakes.</p>
<p>Once you know that historical Rebol was fundamentally broken, there are basically 3 choices:</p>
<ol>
<li>Inventory and address the holes one at a time and try to fix or mitigate them</li>
<li>Ignore the holes and just hope that if you add enough features and integration no one will notice</li>
<li>Turn away and run from the crackpots using it, and work with a more solidly designed language</li>
</ol>
<p>(1) is Ren-C's hard-chosen path. Energy is spent on identifying certain patterns in source that users <em>must</em> be able to write and have work, if the language is to justify its existence at all. While it would be nice if stack traces were beautiful and if building the sources was 100% easy, all of that would be meaningless if the punch line was <em>"oh, and the language this is all supporting doesn't actually work"</em></p>
<p>(2) is chosen by people like Red and <a href="https://github.com/Oldes/Rebol3">Oldes's branch of R3-Alpha</a>, as well as some clones that have popped up over the years.</p>
<p>(3) is probably the most sensible choice, but if I didn't think there was some promise in the language I wouldn't be pursuing (1).</p>
</blockquote>
            <p><small>5 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/my-summary-of-the-big-picture/1792">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/my-summary-of-the-big-picture/1792</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 19:37:40 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1792</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/my-summary-of-the-big-picture/1792.rss">My Summary of the Big Picture</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Turning a Blind Eye to Evaluator &quot;Abuse&quot;</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[hostilefork]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Philosophy</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I've gotten kind of attached to the current look and behavior of AND and OR, which allow short-circuiting even though one would not think the language could (should?) be able to.</p>
<p>It doesn't require simple variables be in a GROUP! on the right hand side.</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; if true and true [print "True"] else [print "False"]
True
</code></pre>
<p>...but a function call has to be.</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; foo: func [x] [
      print "Calling foo!"
      return x &gt; 1000
   ]

&gt;&gt; if false and foo 1020 [print "True!"] else [print "False"]
** Error: words/tuples can't be ACTION! as right hand of OR, AND, XOR

&gt;&gt; if false and (foo 1020) [print "True"] else [print "False"]
False

&gt;&gt; if true and (foo 1020) [print "True!"] else [print "False"]
Calling foo!
True
</code></pre>
<p><em>Note that if the thing to the left of the AND is false, it does not run the code in the GROUP! on the right.</em>  This requires that the right hand side be a quoted parameter convention.</p>
<p>Alternatively we could not quote it, and require the right hand side be in a block:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; if true and [true] [print "True"] else [print "False"]
True

&gt;&gt; if false and [foo 1020] [print "True"] else [print "False"]
False
</code></pre>
<p><strong>But I don't like that.</strong></p>
<p>Alternatively we could say we don't offer this and you always use ALL...maybe with COMMA! and maybe not:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt; if all [true true] [print "True"] else [print "False"]
True

&gt;&gt; if all [false, foo 1020] [print "True"] else [print "False"]
False
</code></pre>
<p>I just don't think that looks as natural.</p>
<h2>It's Like I Said In <a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/speaking-with-tics-should-quoted-arguments-always-be-apostrophed/1359">"Speaking With Tics"</a>...</h2>
<p>If you think seeing a GROUP! on the right of AND and OR that doesn't unconditionally evaluate at the callsite is weird, why are you comfortable with <strong><code>for-each x [1 2 3] [...]</code></strong>?  That didn't unconditionally evaluate x.  Do you expect it to be <strong><code>for-each 'x</code></strong> instead?</p>
<aside class="quote no-group">
<blockquote>
<p>The quoted parameter convention exists to save you the trouble of quoting the callsites. <em>If this isn't what that's for, then what <strong>is</strong> it for?</em></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It's just too nice to be able to say things like <strong><code>if var1 and var2 or (a &gt; b) [...]</code></strong>.</p>
<p>To me, part of what makes the language special is the ability to bend the evaluator to how we want to read code, vs bending code to fit the evaluator.  The existence of mechanics like quoted parameters are there to let this happen.</p>
<p><em>You don't have to use it.</em>  And the ability to switch it to where AND is a prefix operator that does bitwise math is the magic of the freedom of choice.  You can choose to change the definition even on a module-by-module basis, or on a function-by-function basis.</p>
<p>Further: if you're not bending the language, you're probably not really using it.</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://forum.rebol.info/t/turning-a-blind-eye-to-evaluator-abuse/1791">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://forum.rebol.info/t/turning-a-blind-eye-to-evaluator-abuse/1791</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 18:34:57 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">forum.rebol.info-topic-1791</guid>
          <source url="https://forum.rebol.info/t/turning-a-blind-eye-to-evaluator-abuse/1791.rss">Turning a Blind Eye to Evaluator &quot;Abuse&quot;</source>
        </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
